<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truths purchase: or A commoditie, which no man may either neglect to buie, or dare to sell laid forth in two sermons vpon Prov.23.23. by Samuel Hieron minister of the word, at Modburie in Deuon. Very necessary for the times, in which so few seeke after the truth, and so many fall away from the profession and practise of the truth.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851250</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16520</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16520)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1106:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truths purchase: or A commoditie, which no man may either neglect to buie, or dare to sell laid forth in two sermons vpon Prov.23.23. by Samuel Hieron minister of the word, at Modburie in Deuon. Very necessary for the times, in which so few seeke after the truth, and so many fall away from the profession and practise of the truth.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniversitie of Cambridge. 1606. And are to be sold at the signe of the Crowne in Pauls Church-yard by Simon Waterson [in London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher's address from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16520:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16520:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Truths Purchaſe:</hi> OR A Commoditie, which no man may either neglect to buie, or dare to ſell: laid <hi>forth in two Sermons vpon Prov.</hi> 23.23. by Samuel Hieron Miniſter of <hi>the word, at Modburie</hi> in Deuon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Very neceſſary for the times, in which</hi> ſo few ſeeke after the Truth, and ſo many fall <hi>away from the profeſſion and practiſe</hi> of the Truth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuel. 2.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>That which ye haue alreadie, hold faſt till I come.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Cambridge University coat of arms.</figDesc>
               <q>HINC · LVCEM · ET · POCVLA · SACRA</q>
               <q>ALMA MATER CANTABRIGIA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>PRINTED BY IOHN LEGAT, PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Vniverſitie of Cambridge. 1606.</p>
            <p>And are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Crowne in Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church-yard by Simon Waterſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16520:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16520:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull, my very good Ladie, the Ladie Elizabeth Champernowne, of Modburie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, beeing well perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both of your good know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Gods holy <hi>Truth</hi> &amp; of your vnfained affection thereunto, I haue emboldned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſelfe, to preſent you with theſe two Sermons touching <hi>Truth:</hi> yet not for your ſelfe alone, but that from you, they may paſſe to the common vſe of all the Louers of the <hi>Truth.</hi> I doubt not but that your La: doth both ſee, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the miſerie of theſe wretched times, in which Atheiſme, and Policie (falſely ſo called, beeing indeede little better then plaine villenie,) and Temporizing, haue like a canker, fretted out the very heart of Pietie. They are but a fewe, which ſeeke to ſearch out the <hi>Certaintie</hi> in matters of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or which care to haue <hi>ſtabliſhed hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.4. Heb 13.9.</note> and to know preciſely, which is the True God, <hi>Baal</hi> or <hi>the Lord.</hi> Men had rather <hi>halt betweene two opinions,</hi> that ſo they may be for all Times,<note place="margin">1. king. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> then vndergoe the labour of gaining aduiſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. On the other ſide, if we come to theſe, (which yet will needes be religious,) what a wofull
<pb facs="tcp:16520:3"/> falling away doe we behold? In ſome to Poperie, beeing <hi>lead captiue</hi> (God in iuſtice ſending them <hi>ſtrong deluſions</hi>) by thoſe <hi>Falſe brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.6. 2. Theſſ. 2.11. Gal. 2 4.</note> which are <hi>priuily crept</hi> into euery corner, through the remiſſenes of theſe Euill Times. In other ſome to Prophane-neſſe, and to that which is of all other the worſt, <hi>luke-warmenes.</hi> So that we may well ſay,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.16. Iſa. 1.9. Ier 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Except the Lord of Hoſts had reſerued vnto vs euen a ſmall remnant,</hi> culling out (as it were) <hi>one of a citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>and two of a Tribe, as the ſhepheard taketh out of the mouth of a lyon, two legges, or a peece of an eare,</hi> according to the Election of grace, <hi>we ſhould</hi> long ere this <hi>haue beene as Sodom, and like vnto Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha:</hi> we had beene (as it is ſaide of a curſed Tongue) a very <hi>world of wickedneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 3.6.</note> Now, things beeing ſo, there are three duties required of all that feare God. The firſt is, to long for the <hi>Appearing of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> and to crie daily, with the Soules vnder the Altar, <hi>How long Lord, holy and true!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 6.10. Reu. 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>Euen ſo come Lord Ieſus.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, to beware leaſt they <hi>be plucked away with the Errour of the Times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>and fall from their owne ſtedfaſtnes.</hi> The third is, euery man in his place, <hi>earneſtly to contend for the maintenance of the Faith,</hi> and the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel:<note place="margin">Iud: 3.</note> and to be as induſtrious, to <hi>conuert the goers aſtray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5.20. Act. 14.22.</note> and to exhort the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers to <hi>continue in the Faith,</hi> as the Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,<note place="margin">Math. 23.15.</note> both Ieſuits and Seculars are, <hi>to compaſſe ſea and land, to make men of their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.4.</note> and to turne them <hi>from the Truth vnto Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16520:3"/> In deſire to performe ſome part of this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dutie, as I firſt preached theſe Sermons ſo, with the ſame intent I doe now publiſh them. The Text I am ſure, is excellent for the purpoſe, but for my manner of handling it, I leaue it to the cenſure of Gods Church. In Preaching I haue ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted plain-nes, the beſt eloquence, and the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of matters ſo, that thoſe of the loweſt forme may learne ſomewhat, the ſoundeſt and ſurest learning. If any cenſorious diſpoſition ſhall ſay, that theſe things are too meane for this ripe and exquiſite age, let them conſider, that at the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Salomons Temple,<note place="margin">1. k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng. 5.15.</note> there was roome as wel for Burden-bearers, as for other more curious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers: and at the firſt making of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, not onely the Bringers of <hi>blue ſilke, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſcarlet,</hi> but euen the poorer ſort which brought <hi>Goates haire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 25.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>and Rammes skinnes</hi> were accepted. How euer it be, I doe more then hope, that your La. will kindly accept it from me, and entertaine it as a Teſtimonie of my loue, and not ſo onely, but vſe it alſo for your comfort. And ſo praying the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ 3.13.</note> to <hi>make your heart ſtable and vnblameable in holines,</hi> I commit your La. to his grace in Chriſt Ieſus. Modburie. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb. <hi>14. 1606.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your La. in all good affection,</hi> Samuel Hieron.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb facs="tcp:16520:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16520:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Prou. 23.23.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Baie the Truth, but ſell it not.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>The firſt Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſhort ſpeach of Salomons, containeth in it two things: 1. an Iniunction, <hi>Buy the truth:</hi> 2. an Inhibition, <hi>Sell not the truth.</hi> Firſt of the Iniunction. To make way vnto the profitable handling whereof, we are to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine two things: 1. what is the Truth: 2. what it is to <hi>Buy</hi> the ſame.</p>
               <p>Truth is but one, and it is in God,<note place="margin">VVhat is meant by Truth. Quicquid eſt in deo, Deus eſt.</note> and of God; nay it is God himſelfe. For the nature of God is not ſubiect to any attending pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; whatſoeuer is in God, is God. As he is <hi>Mercy</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>Iuſtice</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> it ſelfe, ſo he is alſo, <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe. <hi>God is Truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut 32 4. Ioh. 14.6.</note> ſaith Moſes, and <hi>I am the Truth,</hi> ſaith Chriſt of himſelfe. Yet neuertheleſſe, this Truth which is but one, and is primarily in God, is from him conueied into diuers other things, which in that reſpect are alſo rightly termed <hi>True.</hi> For, as the Sunne is the Fountaine and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16520:5"/> naturall ſeat of Light, yet that Light is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce deriued into many other Bodies naturally fitted to receiue it, which are therefore truly termed <hi>Lightſome;</hi> ſo, though God, is in that ſort the Head &amp; ſpring of all Truth, that he is called euen <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe, yet his <hi>Truth</hi> is communicated vnto other Things alſo: and euery thing is ſo farre forth called <hi>True,</hi> as it is ſquared and made anſwerable vnto that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall <hi>Truth.</hi> And as diuers reſemblances in many glaſſes, being ſet together, doe come all from one and the ſame Face, which is ſet againſt them, ſo all that Truth, which is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, fetcheth it firſt Beginning from the Lord</p>
               <p>Now howſoeuer, the end of all our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, is the vnion of this <hi>Truth</hi> to our vnderſtanding, and the knitting of our ſoules vnto God, (wherein the the very heathen by the Light of nature placed mans Happines,) yet this is not ſo properly that Truth, which is here commended to vs, but rather ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior <hi>Truth,</hi> which is ſubſtituted by God, as a meanes to bring vs vnto himſelfe. And yet, neither is it that <hi>Truth,</hi> which God hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Nature, and naturall things; becauſe, ſo it is that the Creature partaking of Mans corruption,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>is ſubiect to Vanity:</hi> and by that meanes the natiue <hi>Truth</hi> thereof, is ſo tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with lying deceitfulnes, that the Heart of Man (being in it ſelfe a meere lie) is not able to ſeuer each from other, but is rather therby
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16520:5"/> made more vaine, and to <hi>turne the Truth of God,</hi> ſhining therein into a <hi>Lie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.25.</note> So weake an inſtrument is the Booke of nature to beget <hi>Truth</hi> in our heartes.</p>
               <p>There is then another <hi>Truth,</hi> which hath beene framed by God himſelfe, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can deceiue, nor be deceiued, and that is, <hi>The Holy and precious word of the Almightie,</hi> which by the ſpirit of God is called <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.17. Col. 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. Pet. 2.2. Pſal 31.5. 2. Pet. 1.20. Ioh. 14 6. Ioh. 14.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanctifie them with thy Truth, thy word is Truth. The word of Truth which is the Gospell.</hi> And, <hi>the Milke of the word without deceit.</hi> And this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede cannot but be the <hi>Truth.</hi> Firſt, becauſe of the Author of it, which is the God of <hi>Truth.</hi> Secondly, becauſe of the Penmen of it, <hi>Holy men,</hi> which wrote of no priuate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thirdly, becauſe of the confirmer of it, <hi>Chriſt the Truth.</hi> Fourthly, becauſe of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of it, <hi>The Spirit of Truth.</hi> And if it were fitting to the Text, it were eaſie to ſhew, the <hi>Truth</hi> of the Scriptures aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Truthes,</hi> that it is both the moſt auncient <hi>Truth,</hi> and the moſt true Antiquitie. Now, there is yet another deriued <hi>Truth,</hi> which is drawne out of the <hi>Word,</hi> and is, as it were the Briefe and Summary thereof.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.17. Rom. 12.3. Tit. 14. Deu. 34.4.</note> It is that which Paul in one place calleth the <hi>Forme of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> in another place, <hi>the proportion of Faith:</hi> in another, <hi>the Truth which is according to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines.</hi> And this may fitly be compared vnto the mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> vpon which the Lord pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Moſes that from thence he might ſee all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16520:6"/> the borders and limits of the promiſed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan: ſo from this, and by the helpe hereof, a man be able to comprehend with all the Saintes, what is the bredth, and depth, and length, and height of Religion. So then, here is the Iſſue of my ſpeach, that by <hi>Truth</hi> in this place, is meant the <hi>Truth</hi> of Religion, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Rule of <hi>Truth</hi> which is the ſcripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">VVhat it is to Buy the Truth.</note>Now for <hi>Buying,</hi> we muſt vnderſtand, that it is not any making merchandize of the <hi>Truth,</hi> like to that beggerly ſale of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Trumperie; as though a man could by mony, purchaſe the graces of Gods Spirit: which if it were ſo, Chriſt ſhould be prooued a Liar,<note place="margin">Luc. 18.24.</note> who ſaith, that with <hi>difficultie they that haue Riches ſhall enter into the kingdome of God:</hi> whereas, if ſaluation were a mony matter, the Rich were like to ſpeed beſt. But becauſe <hi>Buying</hi> is vſually of things of greateſt coſt, and greateſt neceſſitie, therefore to ſignifie the paines to be taken in this caſe, the ſpirit of God vſeth this word of Buying. Againe, becauſe the end of <hi>Buying</hi> is poſſeſſion, and the end of Poſſeſſion, is vſe; (as Riches is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed to make rich, Apparell to make gay, and ſo in other things;) therefore alſo, the ſpirit of God, to ſhew the care we ought to haue, both to haue the <hi>Truth</hi> in poſſeſſion, and to diuert it to our vſe, hath mentioned <hi>Buying.</hi> So then, this <hi>Buying</hi> of the <hi>Truth,</hi> which is commended here vnto vs, vrgeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16520:6"/> two duties. 1. To labour to haue the <hi>Truth</hi> of Religion ſetled in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that ſo we may be fulfilled with the knowledge of Gods will, in all wiſdome and ſpirituall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. 2. To conuey it thence into our affections, that ſo there may be begotten there, that which Dauid calleth <hi>Truth in the inward parts.</hi> This then is the meaning:<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Buy the Truth,</hi> ſaith Salomon: that is, vſe all diligence,<note place="margin">The ſenſe of the firſt part.</note> ſpare no coſt, refuſe no labour, ſpend your beſt indeauours, to come to the knowledge of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and thereby your ſelues to be transformed into the <hi>Truth;</hi> that you may ſo become true Iſraelites, truly religious.<note place="margin">The diuiſion of it.</note> So that now this firſt member of my Text hath brought forth two Inſtructions: the one is, that we muſt indeuour for the ſetled know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Truth;</hi> the other that we muſt make conſcience of a holy Practiſe, and of obedience to the <hi>Truth:</hi> of theſe two in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And firſt of <hi>Buying</hi> the knowedge of the <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seing it hath pleaſed the wiſdome of God, in this place, to borrow a word from the ordinarie courſes among men, and to cal the ſeeking after the <hi>Truth,</hi> a <hi>Buying,</hi> of the <hi>Truth;</hi> therfore it ſhall not be amiſſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Metaphore, and by examining the vſuall circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of <hi>Buying,</hi> to giue light to the duty recommended here vnto vs.<note place="margin">The particular Branches of this whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> As therefore in all other Bargains, ſo in this Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the <hi>Truth,</hi> theſe things neceſſarily
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16520:7"/> muſt concurre. 1. A deſire of the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. 2. A repairing to the Place, where it is ſet to ſale. 3. A skill to diſcerne, and knowe the goodnes of it. 4. A giuing a price proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the worth and value thereof. 5. A ſtoring it vp for neceſſarie vſes, of all theſe briefly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt Branch.</note>Firſt, there muſt be a deſire of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie: that is plaine in Reaſon. For when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man laieth out his money vpon any thing it proceedeth from a deſire to be the owner of it, and to haue it in poſſeſſion: and ſo the firſt thing in this <hi>Buying,</hi> muſt be that, which the Apoſtle Peter calleth <hi>Deſiring the ſincere milke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2. Iſay. 55.1.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> termeth <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.111. &amp; 174.</note> which Dauid in one place calleth, the <hi>clayming</hi> of the Lord his <hi>teſtimonies as an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage:</hi> in another, the <hi>longing after Gods ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Now the deſire of a commoditie, ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ordinarily from theſe two things. 1. a mans own neceſſitie. 2. the excellencie of the thing it ſelfe. His owne neceſſitie maketh him willing to buy: the excellencie of the thing, maketh him willing to buy, <hi>This,</hi> rather then any other. So that to the end, we may come to this firſt degree, of deſire to <hi>Buy</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> we muſt labour to feele theſe two things. 1. what neede we haue of it. 2. what an excellent thing it is to enioy it. To ſhew our need many things might be alleged: I wil be as briefe in it as I can, becauſe, me think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I doe feele my matter, like to a ſpring,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16520:7"/> the further it goeth, into the more ſtreames to diuide it ſelfe. Man by nature in reſpect of ſpirituall graces, is the pooreſt Creature vnder heauen, he commeth not into the world with a bodie ſo naked, but he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth alſo with a ſoule as vtterly ſtript of all goodnes. To touch onely his penurie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Knowledge. He hath in his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding no true knowledge of God, but onely ſo much left, as may make him inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable before God. And therfore the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth well, ſo often to befoole him, as Salomon doth by name in the booke of the Prouerbes. When man hath to doe with theſe earthly things, he ſeemeth to haue ſome ſharpnes and dexteritie: but when he commeth to ſpirituall things, he is cleane blunted, <hi>They are fooliſhnes vnto him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>neither can he know them.</hi> It is with the Eyes of his ſoule, as it is with the Eyes of his bodie. Our eyes looking vpon the earth, and thoſe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſubſtances, ſeeme quicke and piercing, but let them be turned vp to behold the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Bodie of the Sunne, they are cleane dazeled, and ſeeme to ſee an hundred ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall colours, where there is no colour: ſuch a maze is the wit of man by nature brought into, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to behold &amp; conſider of ſpiritual matters, he wil runne you into milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of abſurdities. Take you Nicodemus, a great wiſe Phariſie, and tell him of the <hi>New birth,</hi> you ſhal ſtrike him into ſuch an amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16520:8"/> that he will crie,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>How can this be?</hi> Goe among the learned Philoſophers, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in their hearing of one Ieſus, who was dead, and now liueth, and of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; what will they ſay? Some will mocke, and call thee <hi>Babler,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 17.</note> that teacheſt ſuch ſtuffe: and they which are the moſt ſtaied among them, will put it to a demurre, they wil heare thee againe of this thing. This is mans natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall pouertie in this caſe. Yea, but will ſome man (perhaps) ſay vnto me: Put caſe, this be true, that I am thus without knowledge of the Truth of my ſelfe, is it any daunger to continue ſo? There be ſome things, which a man hath not, yet can not he be ſaid to want them,<note place="margin">Aliud eſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero, aliud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digere.</note> becauſe he hath no vſe of them: It is one thing to be without a commoditie, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to ſtand in neede of it. To cleare this point therefore in one word: There is as much neede of knowledge, as of ſaluation. If thou haſt need to be ſaued, thou haſt need to haue knowledge alſo. <hi>This is life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3.</note> 
                  <hi>to know &amp;c.</hi> And Paul deſcribing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of a naturall man, putteth theſe two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether;<note place="margin">Eph. 4.18.</note> his <hi>Cogitations are darkened:</hi> and, he is a <hi>ſtranger from the Life of God.</hi> Ignorance and and Deſtruction; Knowledge and Saluation, goe togither. If this be not ſufficient, to ſhew the neceſſitie of Knowledge, I knowe not what may perſwade vs. Now for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of Knowledge, if a man had the Tongue of men and Angels, he could not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16520:8"/> ſpeake ſufficient in commendation of it. The Heathen knew, that Reaſon, is that which maketh man better then a beaſt: and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightening of Reaſon, by Knowledge, is that, which preferreth one man to another. Now, if knowledge be in it ſelfe a thing ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, much more the ſauing knowledge, I meane, the knowledge of Gods <hi>Truth.</hi> This maketh the people of God the wiſeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>This is your wiſdome,</hi> ſaith God,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and your Vnderſtanding.</hi> It bringeth a man to haue a kinde of familiaritie and acquaintance with God himſelfe: yea, it enableth a man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things which <hi>paſſe knowledge,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>the peace of God,</hi> and <hi>the loue of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.7. Eph. 3.19.</note> No meruaile then, though Dauid <hi>reioyced at it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.162.</note> 
                  <hi>as one that findeth great ſpoiles:</hi> and that Paul, did <hi>account all things but dogs-meat, for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent knowledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Phil. 3.8.</note> For both Dauid was thereby <hi>made wiſer then his teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and Paul <hi>by comprehending it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.99. Phil. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>was compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended alſo of his Sauiour.</hi> Thus in part, may we ſee our neede of Knowledge, and the worth of Knowledge, to prepare vs to the purchaſe of Knowledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> To make ſome vſe. This point touching deſire of Knowledge, is worthie the preſſing vpon the Conſciences of men: becauſe the world hath at this day, ſo many ſuch fooles as Salomon ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Pro. 17.16.</note> which haue <hi>a price in their Hand,</hi> but they haue no <hi>heart to get Wiſedome.</hi> They haue the meanes to bring
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16520:9"/> them to the knowledge of the <hi>Truth,</hi> famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, common and eaſie, but haue no affection thereunto. Tell them of Knowledge, it is as the ſinging of ſongs to an heauy heart, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which fitteth not, it hath no relliſh nor ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in the world. Tell the couetous man, the extorting Gentleman, the engroſſing Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, the enhaunſing husbandman, of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, of a ſecret bargaine, of a meanes of gaining, it is like enough, he will ſoone giue thee the hearing, and take thine Information as a fruit of great kindnes: but, talke of the Knowledge of Religion, and of the meanes for attainment to it, thou haſt (as the ſaying is) told a tale to a deafe man,<note place="margin">Surdo cani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> he would as leife thou hadſt kept thy counſell to thy ſelfe. And hence (oh wofull caſe) it is come to paſſe, that groſſe and intolerable ignorance, like a diſeaſe, hath ouerſpread the greateſt part. The multitude know not (as we ſay) the right hand from the left: the beſt of vs be but ſmatterers, and our knowledge little better then <hi>vaine iangling.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.6.</note> There is, I know, ſtore of that knowledge which Micah ſpeaketh of, <hi>The ſtatutes of O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> are ſought for:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mic. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> men are cunning in penall. precepts, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Law-points. There is alſo plentie of the knowledge which Chriſt mentioneth, men can <hi>diſcerne the face of the skie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 16.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ſignes of the Times:</hi> Neither is there any want of that skill which <hi>Amos</hi> toucheth, of <hi>making a ſmall Ephah, and a large ſhekel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Am. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5.</note> Theſe times
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16520:9"/> abound in theſe knowledges: but as for the onely neceſſarie knowledge, the Knowledge of Religion, almoſt no man eſteemeth it; it ſeemeth to vs, as a withered braunch, which hath neither forme nor beautie, we ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, why we ſhould deſire it. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this deadnes and dulnes ariſeth eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, from the want of the feeling of our owne neceſſitie, (for, <hi>the perſon that is full,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 27.7.</note> 
                  <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth an honie combe</hi>) and from our not knowing the worth of Knowledge (for the cocke vpon the dunghill, would rather haue a barley corne, then a diamond) therefore I beſeech you let vs remember, the before-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered matter, touching our owne neceſſitie, that we haue not naturally ſo much as a dramme of true knowledge within vs; and the excellencie of Knowledge, that without it we are but as dead men, ſtrangers from the life of God, without hope, without God in this world. And ſo leauing it to your beſt conſideration, I thus ende this point.</p>
               <p>The next point,<note place="margin">The ſecond Branch.</note> is the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the place of ſale. For, as in our ordinarie buying, it ſuffiſeth not a man, to feele his want of a commoditie, to know the worth of it, and to wiſh the hauing of it, vnleſſe he alſo reſort to the place where it may be had: ſo in this caſe, it is not inough, that we find our ſelues igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, acknowledg our neede of Knowledge, vnleſſe we vouchſafe to repaire thether wher it is ordinarily ſet to ſale, and as it were by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16520:10"/> Proclamation offered to our vſes. Now the vſuall place of ſale, for this commodity of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Knowledge, is the Church, the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Gods Saintes, where the miniſtry of Gods word (the ordinarie meanes of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) is diſpenſed. In the Church, by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of Gods word, we heare Chriſt making a ſolemne <hi>Oyez,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come to me and drinke. Come buy without ſiluer and without mony:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.37. Iſay. 55.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>wherefore doe you lay out ſiluer and not for bread? I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell you to buy of me gold tried by the Fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>that you may be made rich, and rayment, that you may be clothed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalue, that you may ſee.</hi> This is the voice of Chriſt proclayming in the open Market of his Church, and vttering <hi>his voice by the Toppe of the high places,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 9.4.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſo is ſimple let him come hither.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>In me are hid the Treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge. Of my fulnes you may receiue grace for grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.16.</note> So that in the congregation, wher the word is truly &amp; ſincerely preached, as in a Publicke Marte, there is that which is fitting to euery man in euery reſpect. There are the Principles of <hi>Truth,</hi> for Chriſtians of a lower forme: there are deeper points for <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed Wits;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> there is for Magiſtrates, for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, for priuate men, for euery calling: for the you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hee may redres his way, for the old man, to encreaſe in wiſedome, there is truth for the vnderſtanding, truth for the conſcience, truth for the will, truth for the Affections, that ſo a Chriſtian may be <hi>perfite
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16520:10"/> to euery good worke:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.17.</note> whatſoeuer thou doſt lack, there thou ſhalt be ſure to haue it abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſupplied: there thou ſhalt ſee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the <hi>great Myſterie of godlines,</hi> which is, <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh, iustified in the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Gentiles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued on in the world, and receiued vp into glory.</hi> Thus the church is the place, &amp; the preaching of the word is the Treaſure ſubiected to the view, and offered to the vſe of all, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to receiue it. And indeede, herein eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſtandeth the difference betwixt the word Read, &amp; the word Preached. The word read, is as a rich wardrope of a Prince, where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny garments of coſt are folded vp together in a narrow roome, which cannot ſo ſatisfie the beholder, as if the ſame might be ſeueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly layd forth before him, time beeing alſo granted him, to take notice of euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: becauſe, being lapt vp, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſee the whole beautie, and being together, he is not able to obſerue euery ſpecialtie. Euen ſo it fareth with the ſcripture. If a man heare the word read, it cannot but draw him to admire the maieſtie and riches of the Text, and it will caſt ſome glimmering light vpon the vnderſtanding, but when he heareth the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of it laid open by Preaching, it will much more aſtoniſh him; yea it euen raviſh him (as it were,) ſtriking a greater terror in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his conſcience, caſting a clearer light vpon his iudgement, working more mightily vpon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16520:11"/> his affections. This is not ſpoken to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the Reading of the word, or to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the vſe of it out of Gods Church, or to depriue it of that reſpectiue eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which it doth deſerue: nay, it is rather ſpoken to the winning of reuerence thereunto. For indeed, there is no man heareth the word read, more humbly, obſerueth it more heedefully, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth vnto it more affectionately, then he, who by preaching hath beene brought to know the excellencie of the word. So then, here I ſhutte vp this doctrine. He that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to make this purchaſe of the <hi>Truth,</hi> muſt repaire to the place where it is ſet to ſale, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Houſe of God, where the word is truly preached, and ſoundly deliuered.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This point is alſo very neceſſarie to be throughly vrged, in regard of the common ſinne of the world at this day, which is this, the negligent depending vpon the Miniſtery of Gods word. For, howſoeuer ſound, and ſyncere, and often preaching, be not ſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall and common as were to be wiſhed, if God were ſo pleaſed to thruſt out more painfull <hi>Labourers into his harueſt,</hi> yet it is far more generally beſtowed,<note place="margin">Math. 9.38.</note> then obediently and dutifully entertained. For truly, if a man ſhould aske of me, what that thing in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is, which is at this day almoſt in euery place moſt hatefull, moſt abhorred, moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, moſt contemptible, leaſt welcome and leaſt regarded, I know not (I ſpeake vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16520:11"/> how to anſwer more truly, then to ſay it is the Miniſtry and preaching of Gods word. And to the end that I may not ſpeake at Randon but may lay this fault vpon thoſe in whom at is, I will diſtinguiſh thoſe of our Times (to let profeſſed Enemies of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Papiſts, alone) which either come not to the Place of ſale of Truth; or els come as gazers, to looke on, and to fill vp number, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three ſorts. 1. The common proteſtant. 2. The Politician. 3. The proud and ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipted man. By the Common Proteſtant. I vnderſtand ſuch an one, as the Papiſt calleth (in ſcorne ſo ſpeaking of vs all) a Parliament proteſtant, that is, a Time-ſeruer, who look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no further, then to the Law of the Prince, who is readie for any religion, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore indeed of no Religion. Of which humor, there are (the Lord knoweth) infinite multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes at this day, all whoſe Bible is the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Booke, and the Articles of whoſe faith, are grounded vpon poſitiue Iniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Now the common Religion of this common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, I find to be this. He hath a certaine notice of louing God aboue all, and his neighbour as himſelfe, and that he thinketh is as much as he needeth to care for, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner he thinketh with himſelfe: <hi>I keepe my Church, as well as the moſt: I receiue the communion at Eaſter, as becommeth a good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: I liue quietly among my neighbours, and wherein am I now to be found fault withall? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16520:12"/> I am not ouer precize: for I hold that to be more then needes: I am no medler with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that I account to be beyond my reach: once, I am no Papiſt, I content my ſelfe to doe as other doe, and haue no deſire to be ſingular.</hi> Here haue we the right humor of our common men, at this day, this is their Catechiſme, theſe be the very principles of their Religion. Now, hath this man (thinke you) any neede of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? careth he to depend vpon the Miniſtry of the word? Surely no. For he thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of ſo good a Religion, to haue ſo good a faith to God-ward, and to be ſo well min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he hath no minde of Inſtruction. And therefore, he is cleere in it, that it were a great deale better, if there were leſſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: it filleth mens heades full of matters, breedeth diuiſion among neighbours, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth nouelties, and troubleth the whole countrey. Adde hereto (ſaith he) that they themſelues, which preach, cannot agree; and that diſtracteth the people; ſo that their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching might better be ſpared, or at the leaſt, be the leſſe vſed; and what ſhould men doe which haue families to prouide for; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny buſineſſes to diſpoſe of, &amp; much to looke vnto? they cannot intend it, to follow theſe matters ſo hard and hotly as it is required. This is the firſt ſort, that is guiltie of this ſinne, of not caring to frequent Gods cheap-houſe which is his Church, where knowledge of the <hi>Truth,</hi> is by preaching offered vnto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16520:12"/> vs; and the men belonging to it, are ſo humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as I haue deſcribed. The ſecond in this number is the Pollitician, who thinketh all Religion to be but a fable, a matter inuented by wiſer men to hold the vulgar in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to buſie them withall, leaſt they ſhould fall into worſe matters, and runne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to further inconueniences. And therefore tell him of preaching, he laugheth in his ſleeue, accounting them a ſort of ſilly fooles who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it, and making himſelfe beleeue, he is a great wiſe man, becauſe he ſeeth that which the common ſort hath not eſpied. Thus, as the former in a drowſines and hardned ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, contemneth the word, ſo this in a very Atheiſticall and godleſſe profa-neſſe, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it, and maketh a very Ieſt of it. The third in this ranke is the proude conceipted man; who walking in the ſunne is tanned though he meant it not, ſo this, by reading now and then, doth a little ſmell of ſome rudiments of Knowledge, but yet, that litle in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeemeth ſo great that he imagineth that by his priuate Reading at home, he can doe as much and more then by any hearing: and therefore he hath no better opinion of a preacher then the Athenians had of Paul,<note place="margin">Act. 17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>(what will this Trifler ſay?)</hi> So that whereas the Lord tendring our weakenes, and knowing in his wiſedome, what is fitteſt for vs, hath left in his Church the miniſtry of the word for euery mans Inſtruction, he careth not for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16520:13"/> his part, if God had neuer appointed any ſuch meanes, he thinketh he can altogether doe as well without it. This is the proud mans opinion. And thus, by that time you haue referred to euery one of theſe ſort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe that doe by right appertaine to each, and haue ſhuffled in among them, all Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts and ſcorners, and a rabble of other irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons, you ſhall finde the number of carefull comers, to the houſe of God, to buie the Truth at the handes of his Miniſters, to be (as Micah ſpeaketh) like <hi>the ſummer ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1</note> 
                  <hi>and as the grapes of the vintage,</hi> to be but a ſmall number, ſcarſe an handfull in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the multitude. I beſeech you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs learne this leſſon from this place, to loue the gates of the Lords houſe, to let our feet weare out the Treſhold of it, to giue attendance at the Poſts of his doores: and to ſay alſo one to another,<note place="margin">Iſay. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Come, let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And let theſe carnall reaſonings goe, as to ſay, (looking but to the face and gifts of the Preacher) what is he, that he ſhould teach me, and why may I not profit as well by ſome other courſe? but remember, that the <hi>Power of God is made perfect through weakenes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 12.9.</note> and that as it was a greater honour to God, to ouerthrow the walles of Iericho, by the noiſe of rams-hornes, then if it he had done it by Canon-ſhot;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> ſo it is more for Gods glorie, by the <hi>Fooliſhnes of Preaching to ſaue thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16520:13"/> then if an Angel ſhould deſcend from heauen to inſtruct, nay, then if the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould ſpeake with ſome audible voice to conuert vs. And ſurely, as in Buying and ſelling, that Bargaine is by law moſt warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which is made in open market; ſo I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that knowledge moſt acceptable vnto God, and moſt like to receiue a bleſſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, which is gotten publikely, by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie courſe appointed for that purpoſe. Howſoeuer, I doubt not, but as a man hauing publikely bought a commoditie, may pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately husband it, to his owne beſt behoofe, ſo that which is deliuered openly may, (nay ought) by priuate reading, praier, meditation, and conference, be encreaſed. And thus much for this ſecond Branch.</p>
               <p>The third thing in this Purchaſe of <hi>Truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The third Branch.</note> is, Skill to diſcerne. For as in Buying, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſo many counterfeit Wares, of the mingling good with bad, and the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the world, it is good for a man to haue skill to preſerue himſelfe from coſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and from cauſe-les expenſe vpon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable goods: ſo in labouring after Knowledge, in reſpect of ſo much blending mans inuentions with holeſome doctrine, it is requiſite, that we be able to put a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt holy, and corrupt, true and falſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and vnprofitable Teaching. And this is a thing, which the Scripture alſo in many places requireth of vs. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the ſpirits,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16520:14"/> Iohn,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.1. 1. Theſ. 5.21. Pro. 14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>whether they be of God or no. Try all things,</hi> ſaith Paul: and he is a foole, ſaith Salomon, that <hi>will beleeue euery thing:</hi> and for this cauſe the noble men of Beraea are commended, becauſe hearing the Apoſtles preach, they <hi>ſearched the ſcriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> And our Sauiour hath pronounced it generally of all his ſheepe, that they <hi>know his voice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and will not follow a ſtranger, but flee from him &amp;c.</hi> For howſoeuer we doe vrge all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent reſpect vnto the preaching of the word, as to the Ordinance of God, for the <hi>gathering together of his Saints, and for the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the bodie of Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph 4.12.</note> yet we abhorre that Popiſh tyrannizing ouer the faith of our Hearers, as though we would binde them to giue credit to euery thing we ſpeake, becauſe we ſpeake it:<note place="margin">Authoritate nomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s. Amb. in 1. The. cap. 5.</note> We know, that if he were an Angel from heauen, that ſhould come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, yet his doctrine muſt be brought to the <hi>Law</hi> and to the <hi>Teſtimonie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay. 8.20.</note> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh, and if he be found to ſwerue from that holy doctrine which we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8. 2. Ioh. 10.</note> he muſt goe for <hi>accurſed,</hi> and, <hi>bid him not ſo much as God ſpeede,</hi> ſaith S. Iohn. And this skilfulnes and Abilitie to diſcerne, as it is euer neceſſarie, ſo now eſpecially. Firſt of all, becauſe there are (that I may ſtill follow the language of my Text) ſo many pety-chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I meane, ſo many priuie workmen, who are all guided with the ſpirit of the Beaſt, ſent out and ſet on worke, by that Antichriſt,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16520:14"/> that man of Rome, who are crept almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery corner, and vnder pretence of their deuotions and <hi>Voluntarie Religion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of minde,</hi> inſinuate and winde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into many mens Affections, drawing ſome to traiterous diſloyaltie, ſome to ſetled Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, others to indifferent and depending vncertentie, that ſo they may fit and prepare them for that day, which they haue long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and I pray God they may ſtill with wearied eyes, and languiſhing ſpirits awaite for. Now to the ende, that theſe falſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.4.</note> which are come in <hi>priuily to bring vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bondage,</hi> may not carie vs away with droſſe for ſiluer, glittering ſhewes for a golden ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, counterfait profeſſion, for ſound Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we had neede to labour and pray for diſcerning ſpirits. Secondly, this abilitie to diſcerne is neceſſarie, in regard of ſo many dangerous and infectious Bookes, which (I know not by whoſe default) are ſparſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into all partes, tending to the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the preſent ſtate, and of our holy Religion, and to the working of mens affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to a more tolerable opinion (if not a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall embracing) of Poperie. Thirdly, this skill is no leſſe neceſſarie, in reſpect of ſo much corrupt Preaching, both in manner and matter. Firſt, for the manner of Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, it is an ordinarie thing with many men of giftes, to ſcorne to ſeeme to <hi>Know nothing but Chriſt, and him crucified,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2.</note> and to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16520:15"/> thinke baſely of the plaine <hi>euidence of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> And therefore, they haue more care to abound with excellent words, &amp; <hi>with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing ſpeeches of mans wiſedome,</hi> then to ſpeak to the conſcience of their Hearers; ſo that in this reſpect, we had neede to be wiſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne, leaſt our faith ſhould be in <hi>the wiſdome of man rather then in the power of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.5.</note> Againe, for the matter of preaching, it is now almoſt in religion and diuinitie, as in the matter of Apparell; every yeare bringeth a new faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then (becauſe of the loue which men haue to noveltie) that, is thought to be the moſt hanſome, moſt thriftie, and moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table faſhion, only indeed becauſe it is the neweſt, and ſo, euery yeare almoſt, we heare of ſome new opinion or other, raked out of the dunghill of Poperie, and a new gloſſe ſet vpon it,<note place="margin">2. Tim 4.3.</note> and by and by it is entertained, men that haue itching Eares are readie to liſten to it, &amp; are ſoone wrought to embrace it. This is the great pollicie of the Deuill, neither is there any thing, by which he doth more harme, by which he killeth more ſoules then by this meanes. When the Lord was purpoſed to bring a plague vpon Ahab, the Scripture deſcribeth him as it were ſitting in counſell, what might be the next way to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow him. At laſt, when one had ſaid on this manner, and another on that, there came forth a <hi>Spirit and ſtood before the Lord, and ſaid, I will entiſe him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. king. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Lord ſaid vnto him,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16520:15"/> Wherewith? And he ſaid, I will goe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and be a falſe ſpirit in the mouth of all his Prophets: Then he ſaid, Thou ſhalt entiſe him, and thou ſhalt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile.</hi> Thus it appeareth, that the moſt ſpeedy way which Satan, beeing put to his choice, hath, to doe miſchiefe, is to ſende ſpirits of Error, priuily to bring in damnable and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous opinions. And ſurely it is iuſt with God, to giue vs ouer to be ſeduced, becauſe we <hi>haue not receiued the loue of his Truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſſ 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>that we might be ſaued.</hi> So then, that neither inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating Ieſuites may deceiue vs, not dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous bookes empoiſon vs, nor fantaſticall Teachers beguile vs, nor corrupt Doctours <hi>carrie vs away with euery winde of Doctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph 4 14.</note> it ſtandeth vs vpon to labour to abound with ſpirituall wiſedome, and vnderſtanding, that we may diſcerne betwixt Light and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Truth and falſehood, leaſt, leauing to follow Chriſt, as a ſhepheard to the fold, we go after Antichriſt, as a Butcher to the ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The Vſe of this point is, to reprooue two faults eſpecially. 1. The wilfulnes of ſome. 2. The vnskilfulnes of other-ſome. For the firſt, many there are in this naughtie &amp; croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation, who becauſe of the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is in the Teaching of ſome, (which implieth a poſſibilitie to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) and becauſe of the ſhew of difference in ſome things, which ſeemeth to be among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-ſome, I ſay in theſe reſpects, ſome there
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16520:16"/> are, who are growne to that peeuiſhnes, that they reſolue with themſelues, that it is the beſt courſe to heare none. We cannot tell, ſay they, whom to beleeue, they are at uari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance among themſelues, and therefore till they doe better accord, it will be the ſafeſt, and wiſeſt way, either not to heare, or not to credit any. This is the wayward humor of many in this Age. Their folly (as to me ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) may well be manifeſted, by vrging the preſent ſimilitude of <hi>Buying.</hi> If a man wanting meat, drinke and raiment, and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and being perſwaded to ſupply himſelfe out of the market, from thoſe which ſell, ſhould make this Anſwere. <hi>The world is ſo full of deceipt, that a man knoweth not whom to truſt; they which ſell, many of them will beguile their owne fathers, if they ſhould chaffer with them; and the trickes and deuiſes which tradſemen haue are ſo many, that it is twentie to one but a man ſhall be cooſened, I had rather therfore goe neere the wind, and want neceſſarie prouiſion, then put it to the hazard of Buying:</hi> If I ſay, a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, ſhould plead thus, what would we thinke of him, but that either he were very fooliſh or verie froward? And ſo we well might; becauſe, we know, the fraud of others muſt be preuented, rather by care and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, and not vſed as an occaſion for a man to abridge himſelfe of his neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Is not he then as much a foole, who wanting the ſauing knowledge of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16520:16"/> 
                  <hi>Truth,</hi> and being called vpon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to the houſe of God, where the Meanes is offered freely vnto him, ſhall p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead ſtrait the deceiuablenes of falſe doctrine, the corruption of many Teachers, the ſhew and appearance of contrarieties, as though he were therefore to depriue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of the neceſſarie foode of his ſoule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may be, that through want of care, inſtead of being fedde, he may be poiſoned. We know rather, that he ought to be, the more diligent in praier, the more ſtudious in the ſcripture, that ſo when he commeth to buy the <hi>Truth</hi> he may not be deceiued. Thus this point meeteth with this humour of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. Now for the vnskilfulnes of men, this point doth alſo make againſt it exceedingly. It is too true of the greateſt part of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers at this day,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.20. Phil. 1.10.</note> that they are <hi>Children in Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding:</hi> they want that Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which Paul ſpeaketh of to, diſcerne <hi>things that differ one from an other:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.6.</note> they are like a waue of <hi>the ſea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>euery Wind of Doctrine</hi> is readie to ouer blow them; their <hi>Heartes</hi> are not <hi>ſtabliſhed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5 14.</note> they haue no <hi>exerciſed Wits.</hi> They will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to crie Hoſanna to Chriſt to day, and to bid <hi>Crucifie him</hi> to morrow; they are like thoſe of <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> who at the firſt admired Paul, and made a God of him, but with the turning of an hand, by the counſell of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Iewes, they drew him out of the Citie and ſtoned him;<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> ſo vnſtable and vnſetled are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16520:17"/> the moſt of vs at this day, that a man may perſwade any thing ſauing that which ought to be beleeued. Who almoſt is ſo skilfull and experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, as to know euen in the principall matters, and moſt neceſſarie points of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, what is to be held as <hi>Truth,</hi> and to be deteſted as an Error? to be able to ſay pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily; this I am ſure is true in Religion, and I will (by the grace of God) liue and die in it; this is an Error, &amp; I hope neuer to yeeld vnto it? You will ſay (perhaps) this is inough for Preachers. Oh, belooued, I ſay as Moſes did, <hi>I would all the Lords people were Prophets,</hi> I would we were al thus cunning; nay I would men were,<note place="margin">Num. 11.29.</note> or could be perſwaded, that this is a dutie, to ſtriue to come to a ſetled certen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie herein. Then ther were much hope of the perpetuating of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then we need neuer feare the reſtabliſhment of Poperie, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, I am ſure would giue vp the Ghoſt. Well, you ſee, the <hi>Truth</hi> muſt be bought, for ſhame we cannot deny it. In <hi>Buying,</hi> we may be ouereached; in reaſon we cannot ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; therefore we ſhould alſo be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to be ſo without Reaſon, as not to thinke it reaſon, to labour with the Lord by Praier, to lead vs into all <hi>Truth,</hi> that ſo we may grow in the <hi>Truth,</hi> and continue firme in the <hi>Truth</hi> vnto the end. And this is an End of the third Branch.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth Branch.</note>The fourth Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in making this Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the <hi>Truth,</hi> is, to giue the price propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16520:17"/> to the value of the Commoditie, which is indeede the very Act of Buying; the other three, which I haue named hitherto, are but preparatiues to <hi>Buying.</hi> For though a man feeleth his owne want, commeth to the place of ſale, trieth and examineth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie which is for his neceſſitie, yet he is not ſaid to haue bought, till he haue paid the price at which the thing is rated. All the while before, he is ſaid to be but a chapman, and many do all the former oftentimes, who haue no great diſpoſition to buie. So fareth it in our cuſtomarie <hi>Buying,</hi> and ſo it is in this caſe. It is neceſſarie for a man to feele the want of Knowledge, to come to the place of Knowledge, to examine that which is profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him, but yet he hath not followed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons counſell as he ought, vntill he haue paide the price alſo. Now the price (as I told you) is not money (for,<note place="margin">Act. 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy money periſh with thee,</hi> which art of that opinion:) but the price is this, to preferre it in account and eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before all Things, and ſo to make it our chiefeſt labour to attaine it. You ſhall ſee this prooued. <hi>If thou ſeekeſt knowledge as ſiluer, and ſearcheſt for her as for Treaſure,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 2.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>then thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vnderſtand the Feare of the Lord. The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen is like to a Merchant-man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 13.45.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſeeketh good pearles, who hauing found a pearle of great price, went and ſold all that he had, and bought it. The kingdome of Heauen ſuffereth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, and the violent take it by force.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 11.12.</note> Will you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16520:18"/> haue examples?<note place="margin">Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I count all things loſſe</hi> (ſaith Paul) <hi>for the excellent Knowledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> and a little after in the ſame chapter he compareth himſelfe to a man in a race, who, partly to ſignifie his deſire of the prize, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to helpe himſelfe in running, leaneth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his running:<note place="margin">ver. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſo (ſaith he) <hi>I forget that which is behind, bending forward to that which is before, I follow &amp;c.</hi> And if a man might goe further, Dauid may ſeeme herein a little to haue gone beyond him. <hi>I opened my mouth, and panted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.131.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe I loued thy Commandements.</hi> Dauid was ſo hotte, and egre in this purſuit, that he was euen breathleſſe, he was faine to gape for a new ſupplie of winde. Thus theſe places, and theſe examples, I hope, doe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prooue this point, namely, that the price to be giuen for the Knowledge of the <hi>Truth,</hi> is to ſet no price vpon it, but to eſteeme it aboue all price, and to account that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is too deare, no trauaile too much, no paine too great for the attainment thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The vſe of this point is neceſſarie alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church of God is at this day ſo ful of Huckſters, which are euer cheapening, but buie nothing: that is, as S. Paul ſpeaketh, <hi>are euer learning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and yet neuer come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> They come to church, and heare, and goe home, and come againe, and heare againe, and ſo goe round, like a Horſe in a mill, and are yet neuer the nearer.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16520:18"/> They are like the fiſh in the ſea, which liue in the ſalt water, and are yet neuer the ſalter: ſo they heare the word, which is the <hi>ſalt of the Earth,</hi> and yet are ſtill vnſeaſoned.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> Now the ſpeciall reaſon of it is, becauſe they be no franke chapmen; they would haue too good a peniworth, they will buie the <hi>Truth</hi> vnder foote, or they will none of it. If to heare now and then, and in hearing, now and then to hearken, and ſo an ende, and ſome ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall performances will doe it, they will be content to be at the coſt, otherwiſe they wiſh you a better chapman, the ware is too deare. If you tell them of often Hearing, and of keeping their hearts and eares together from the beginning of a Sermon to the end, of priuate Meditation, of conference, of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before to prepare them, of praier after to ſtrengthen them, of redeeming the Time, and ſetting ſome part apart for ſuch holy purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they make you anſwer, that you ſet your Knowledge at too high a rate, and vnleſſe they ſhall find you more reaſonable, and that they may haue it with leſſe paines, leſſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance, leſſe diſgrace, they are content to let it goe, or els, as men doe when things are too deare, they will take the leſſe, and a ſmaller portion ſhall ſuffice them. To ſhake off this dulnes, and backwardnes, and that men may learne to be aſhamed of this niggardize, to ſtand offering and offering, and like to neere fellowes, to be loth (as it were) to come off
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16520:19"/> with the other penie, I pray you let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the price which the Lord hath ſet, and whereof there is not one haire to be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It muſt ſuffer violence, it muſt be moſt of all eſteemed, and ſought for firſt of all, it muſt be ſtriuen for, and ſtudied about, and cared for exceedingly. If we be not willing to giue this price, we doe but peſter Gods houſe, it is in vain for vs to make a ſhew, and to come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Gods people vſeth to come: God can not endure to be dallied withall, either goe through with him, or neuer begin with him. And to comfort thee, take this with thee: the commoditie is better then it maketh ſhew for: and when thou haſt once gotten it, and viewed it better, thou wilt ſay as Dauid, <hi>The lines are fallen vnto me in a pleaſant place,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.6.</note> 
                  <hi>yea I haue a faire heritage:</hi> and thou ſhalt haue more <hi>ioy of heare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.7.</note> then the Rich worldings haue when their <hi>wine and oyle aboundeth.</hi> Thus much of this point, which is the very act of <hi>Buying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fift Branch.</note>The laſt circumſtance, in this Bargaine of <hi>Truth,</hi> is to ſtore it vp. For as, bought com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities are ſafely diſpoſed, and ſaid vp, till Time and occaſion ſhall offer vſe: ſo gotten Knowledge, muſt be reſerued in the Store-houſe of the Memorie, that when any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of vſe ſhall be offered, it may be at hand, either for the Triall of a <hi>Truth,</hi> or for a Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in life.<note place="margin">Pro. 4.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Let not the words of my mouth,</hi> ſaith the wiſedome of God, <hi>depart from thee, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16520:19"/> keepe them in the midſt of thy heart.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>19.11.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue hidde thy promiſes in my heart,</hi> ſaith Dauid: and Marie is commended,<note place="margin">Luc. 2.19.31.</note> becauſe ſhee <hi>kept Chriſts ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and pondered them in her heart.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede there is great reaſon, why this of Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp, ſhould be added to all the former. For though a man ſhould deſire the <hi>Truth</hi> earneſtly, care to heare it diligently, diſcerne it wiſely, obtaine it painefully, yet it will litle auaile, if it doe ſtrait runne from him, if it be as ſoone forgotten, as gotten, if it be not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, and ſetled,<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> that ſo it may <hi>dwell plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly</hi> in the heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The vſe hereof in a word is this, to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſtirre vs vp to beware of a common Euill, which is, to leaue the word there, where we heard it, and ſeldome or neuer to call our ſelues to an account, how and in what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure we haue profited, how our iudgements haue beene ſetled, our affections reformed, our conſciences comforted, by that which we haue heard. Learne a ſimilitude from <hi>Buying.</hi> A man, who hath beene at the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, or at the Merchants ſhoppe, and hath there laid out his money, when he returneth home, he will beginne to call himſelfe to an account, to ſee what he hath laid out, where the things are, which he hath bought, and whether he hath not loſt any thing thereof: and if he haue, he will returne againe, to the place where he bought it, to trie, if he left it not there, and in the way he will enquire of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16520:20"/> euery one he meeteth, if they haue not found ſuch or ſuch a thing, and will neuer be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, vntill he haue found the ſame. It ſhould be ſo, with vs, in this caſe. When we come from Gods houſe, whether we went to <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Truth,</hi> after our returne, we ſhould finde a time to keepe (as it were) an Audit, with our ſelues, to ſee what we haue gained, by that daies hearing, and ſhould endeauour to trie our ſelues from point to point: If we find ſome things forgotten, returne we muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to the Miniſterie of the word, to ſee if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſe God, that the ſame things may be againe deliuered, &amp; inquire of our friends &amp; familiars which were there, whether they can helpe vs in recounting thoſe things, which through infirmitie haue eſcaped vs. Thus Knowledge would grow vp, Religion would thriue amongſt vs, and we ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in ſpirituall vnderſtanding, and ſo both thoſe which teach vs, ſhould be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and we our ſelues ſhould exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be comforted. One ſpeciall reaſon which may mooue vs to this care of ſtoring vp knowledge in Religion, is the poſſibilitie of a famine of the word of God amongſt vs. We read,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.</note> that when there was a famine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching in Egypt, Ioſeph aduiſed Pharaoh to make prouiſion before hand in the ſeuen plentifull yeares, and to lay vp corne againſt the time of Penurie. This was good Pollicie in humane reaſon. It ſhall be no leſſe good
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16520:20"/> Policie in Religion, now in theſe times, in which the word of God is plentifull, and we haue it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon amongſt vs, to treaſure vp knowledge againſt the daies of want, we hauing giuen the Lord, ſo great cauſe to take away his word from vs, and to giue it to a nation that ſhal bring forth better fruits then we haue done. So that indeede (conſidering our intolerable contempt of Gods <hi>Truth,</hi> and our generall lothing this heauenly Manna) it is rather to be wondred, that the Lord hath hitherto for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne vs, then to be preſumed, that we ſhall ſtill ſcape away vnpuniſhed. I beſeech you therefore, let vs now play the the good husbands, and beſtirre vs, and euen engroſſe, as much knowledge in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as is poſſible, that ſo if ever ſuch a heauie time ſhould come (as Lord, if it be thy will, ever keepe it from vs) we may be able to ſpeake a word in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to our owne ſoules, and to be a comfort alſo, and an inſtruction vnto others: leaſt then, many of vs, which now will ſcarſe ſteppe out of our doores to heare, ſhall be glad to runne from North to Eaſt, but ſhall not finde it. This may be, and I hope will be, a motiue to vs, to Buie the <hi>Truth,</hi> while the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket laſteth, and to lay it vp in ſtore againſt the Times of wofull neceſſitie. Thus (as I could) I haue endeauoured to diſcouer vnto you, the whole My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of this Bargaine of <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo farre forth as it concerneth our care, in labouring to be grounded in the Knowledge of Religion.</p>
               <p>Nowe before I doe diſmiſſe this point, it might not be amiſſe (perhappes) to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to thoſe which are the Lordes Officers,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16520:21"/> (as it were) in the ſelling of his <hi>Truth</hi> vnto the people, I meane the Miniſters of the Goſpell. For ſure, by iuſt proportion, everie one of theſe circumſtances, ſeemeth to vrge a dutie vpon them. Firſt of all, if the people, muſt haue a deſire to get Knowledge, it is meete, that they ſhould haue a deſire to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part Knowledge. And it is a notable thing, it a Miniſter,<note place="margin">Iob. 32.19.</note> when he is like vnto the veſſell to which <hi>Elihu</hi> compared himſelfe which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no vent,<note place="margin">Ier. 20.9.</note> is readie to burſt; ſo that the ſpirit within him, compelleth him, and <hi>the Word in his Heart, is as a Burning Fire ſhut vp in his Bones, ſo that he cannot ſtay:</hi> And ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, it is a miſerable thing when his bowels are ſhutte vp, and he hath no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in regard of the neceſſities, of gods people. So then, let this, that the people muſt haue a deſire to learne, teach vs to be of Pauls mind,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.11.</note> euen <hi>to long to beſtow ſome ſpirituall gift among them.</hi> Secondly, they muſt come to the Church, the Place of ſale: there muſt be ſome body there to diſcouer the treaſures of Gods houſe, to open the myſteries of Godlineſſe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and therfore it would make ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſh his head were ful of water, and his eies a Fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Teares, to ſee the ſtate of many Churches. Becauſe my Text ſpeaketh of Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I know not whereto better to compare them, then to ſome old Townes, which haue had yearely faires in them, and are now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied, and growne out of vſe: you ſhall ſee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16520:21"/> vpon the day in which their faires were wont to be kept, they will hang out a glooue or ſome ſuch teſtimonie of ſuch a meeting, but not one whit of ware is there to be ſold: ſo in many Churches, you ſhall ſee a Pulpit, a place for a ſpeaker, and another for hearers, bur it is bu for a ſigne, he which commeth thither <hi>to buy the Truth,</hi> is like to haue but a reaſonable Bargaine. Thirdly, as the People muſt labour for diſcerning ſpirits, ſo the Preachers, muſt ſtudie to ſpeake iudicially, that they may ſay as Chriſt ſaid to Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, <hi>we ſpeake that we know;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.11.</note> leaſt they be an occaſion of falling vnto any. Fourthly, as the people muſt equall the price to the worth of the thing, that is, muſt ineſtimably value that which is taught, ſo the Preachers ought to beware of doing Gods <hi>Buſines negligently,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> of ſlight and ſuperficiall performance of ſo waightie a matter. It is generally a fault with vs, that the world hath ſo beguiled and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled vs, that it maketh vs ſo ſlenderly to prepare our ſelues to the duties of our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Miniſtry; as though to preach, were a buſines but by the way: and that cauſeth our Preaching to cary the leſſe Maieſtie and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie with it, becauſe the wiſer ſort of our hearers, doe perceiue, that we are often put to our ſhifts, and doe make Preaching to be but an exerciſe by the glaſſe, which time if we can by any meanes fill vp,<note place="margin">Ad c. epfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dram</note> we hold it to be ſufficient; well, if our hearers muſt buy our
<pb facs="tcp:16520:22"/> Sermons at ſo deare a rate, let vs indeauour that they may be worth the <hi>Buying.</hi> Laſtly, as the people muſt ſtore vp knowledge, and that now eſpecially, becauſe we know not how neere the dearth is; ſo we muſt alſo now chiefly, bring out of our <hi>Treaſures both new &amp; old,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.52.</note> and not be wanting by our forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to provoke them to diligence in this caſe, remembring what Chriſt ſpeaking tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching himſelfe hath laid vpon vs all,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.4.</note> namely <hi>to worke the workes of him that ſent vs while it is Day; the night commeth when no man can worke.</hi> Thus much I thought good by the way to adde, touching thoſe, whom the Lord hath deputed to the ſeruice of his Church, that we may all <hi>take heed to our Miniſtry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>which we haue receiued, to fulfill it.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The ende of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16520:22"/>
               <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Prou. 23.23.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Buie the Truth, but ſell it not.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I purpoſe not to enter into any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe repetition, of the points taught out of this place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, at the Time of my laſt beeing here; yet for order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodes ſake, that it may appeare, how I make my two Sermons to agree, and to follow, the one directly vpon the other, I muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreat you to remember with me thus much; that, as this Text was diuided into two parts, 1. an Iniunction: 2. an Inhibition; ſo the former part was cut into two members: the one, concerning the ſetled knowledge of the <hi>Truth:</hi> the other, touching a holy practiſe, and obedience to the <hi>Truth.</hi> The firſt of theſe two, was the matter and ſubiect of the laſt Sermon, the latter muſt hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt roome in this exerciſe.</p>
               <p>The perfection and good of euery Action is the Ende of it: becauſe, whatſoeuer we
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16520:23"/> doe attempt and vndertake, ſomething there is which we doe aime at therein, which is by many degrees to be preferred before the meanes leading thereunto. As it is in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, ſo is it in the <hi>Buying</hi> of the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of the doctrine which is according to godlines. For it is not therefore onely to be purchaſed, that by it the Miſt of ignorance in the vnderſtanding part might be diſpelled, but alſo that thereby, the Will might be ſtrengthened, the Affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtreightened, the Conſcience purged, the Outward man refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; ſo the very Bodie of Falſhood which <hi>the Father of lies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.45.</note> hath begotten in vs might be vtterly deſtroied. Well then, that we may profit by the handling of this point. I will take this Courſe: I will ſhew you firſt, what this ſecond and inferior <hi>Truth</hi> is, which muſt be had alſo to the making vp of this full Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe. Secondly, I will declare the neceſſitie of it. Thirdly, I will applie the ſame to our vſe.</p>
               <p>And firſt of all, that we may vnderſtand, what this kind of <hi>Truth</hi> is, which from the vnderſtanding, is deriued into the whole man, and diuerted to the ordering and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment thereof, I take it the beſt way will be, a little to take view of that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie thereto, which beeing aright concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of, will giue a better light vnto this. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in one of his Pſalmes, maketh mention of a certaine Guile, which he calleth a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16520:23"/> Guile; Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the man its whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</hi> And,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.2.</note> 
                  <hi>our Sauiour commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Nathaneel</hi> in theſe termes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold an Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite in whome there is no Guile.</hi> When we ſhal vnderſtand what this <hi>Spirituall Guile</hi> is, we ſhall the better iudge what this other <hi>Truth</hi> is, which my intent is to vrge in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spirituall Guile</hi> may be in generall thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: It is a kinde of double dealing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and a mans owne ſelfe, in the things which doe concerne his ſoule. It hath many Branches, which beeing opened will giue a fuller &amp; cleerer light vnto the whole; you may (if you pleaſe) ſuppoſe this <hi>ſpirituall guile</hi> generally named, to be (as it were) the Coate of fig-leaues, which Adam made for himſelfe when he had firſt ſinned, wherewith to hide himſelfe from God; and the opening of the particulars, (into which I am now to enter,) to be (as it were) the ripping of that coate, and the ſundring of each leafe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſame is patched together. The firſt branch then of this <hi>Guile,</hi> is a conceipt of a mans owne good Eſtate for ſpirituall things: an opinion that all in him is well, &amp; nothing to be found fault withall. Such a conceipt it ſeemeth to me, that Paul had of himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his conuerſion: <hi>I once was aliue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>without the law:</hi> that is;<note place="margin">Rom 7.9.</note> before I tooke a fuller view of my ſelfe, in the glaſſe of Gods Law, I deemed my ſelfe perfite, I was ſo <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of my fathers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that I ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16520:24"/> that I was a man out of the reach of all exception. Such an one alſo, was the proud Phariſie, who ſtood prating, and telling God a Tale of his owne good deedes.<note place="margin">Luc. 18.11.</note> Such an one alſo,<note place="margin">Math 9.13.</note> are they whom Chriſt calleth <hi>Righteous</hi> in that ſaying, <hi>I came not to call the Righteous;</hi> that is, men that are ſo in their own ſeeming. And euen ſuch, the greateſt part of vs are at this day,<note place="margin">Pſa. 10.3.</note> lying to our owne hearts, <hi>bleſſing</hi> our ſelues, as Dauid ſpeakes. So that it is even the hardeſt matter in the world, to perſwade vs, or to beate it into vs, that our naturall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, in regard of the abundance of in-borne corruption, is ſo lamentable, ſo wofull, and ſo deepely to be pitied, as indeed it is. And that maketh many carnall men, euen to won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der what Preachers meane, when they ſpeake ſo vehemently touching the miſerie of mans nature, and the extreame danger in which he ſtandeth thereby. Hence alſo it is, that the offers of Gods mercie in Chriſt are ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfully entertained, and ſo commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected: men not knowing their owne neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie doe deſpiſe the Riches of Gods boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> and euen <hi>tread vnder foote the Sonne of God.</hi> The ſecond branch of this <hi>Spirituall Guile,</hi> is to extenuate and leſſen thoſe ſinnes which we cannot but acknowledge. As namely, when the word working vpon the conſcience, hath made a man euen in deſpite of his own heart, to confeſſe himſelf in ſome things guilty, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to find this ſhift, that yet they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16520:24"/> are ſmall and pettie offences, they are no hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, nor bloody ſinnes, and therefore there is no ſuch danger in them, as that they ſhould aske ſo ſpeedie, and ſo deepe repentance. This falſe Tricke we read Saul plaied.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.</note> When he had preuented the appointment of Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el for ſolemne ſacrificing at <hi>Gilgal,</hi> (which how great a ſinne it was, the reproofe and puniſhment of it doe declare) yet Saul being challenged for it, and not able to denie the fact, extenuated the matter in theſe tearmes, <hi>I was bold, &amp;c.</hi> he was content to acknowledge it a little ſlippe, but loth to yeeld it, to be a matter of that hainouſnes, that Samuel would make it to be. And this is the very conceipt, which men haue of many ſinnes at this day, as of Ieſting, fooliſh Talking, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpeaking, ſwearing, dalliance, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Gaming, Reuelling, Sabaoth-breaking, which though they be in their owne nature verie great ſinnes, yet the outrage of theſe worſt times, hath made them ſo common, that the commonnes, hath much abated the vglines of them in mens Opinion. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when men are dealt with, for any of theſe or the like, and cannot but confeſſe their own guiltineſſe, yet they will ſay, <hi>I hope this is no ſuch great offence, I pray God I neuer doe worſe, you neede not make ſo great a matter of ſo ſmall a treſpaſſe, and I truſt God will not be ſo extreame for euery Trifle.</hi> This is a ſecond branch of this <hi>Guile.</hi> The third branch is, a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16520:25"/> Lying ſhirt, which Satan hath furniſhed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny withall, which is this; to thruſt themſelues in among the multitude, and to thinke by that meanes to eſcape away vneſpied, or at the leaſt, the leſſe blamed. So at this day, the ſuperſtitious and ceremonious people, which place all religion, in outward obſervances, doe ſhroud themſelues vnder their fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, couer the matter with the name of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and with the practiſe and example of the Multitude; they are content to doe as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe, and therewith they hope to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed. In like ſort many taken in the common ſinne of this Age, I meane, Adultery, when they cannot but confeſſe it, then this is their Plea, that they be not the firſt; as though it were wiſedome for them to goe to hell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the way thither is a much travailed way, in which a man ſhall never miſſe much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Vnder this kind of <hi>Guile,</hi> may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all ſuch courſes, the lawfulneſſe whereof, men doe ground onely vpon Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, being of the ſame mind for matters of godlines and religion, that <hi>Chuſai</hi> would ſeeme to be in ſtate matters vnto <hi>Abſalom, Whom this people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 26.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and all the men of Iſrael chuſe, his will I be, and with him will I dwell.</hi> So ſay they, <hi>Looke which way the moſt goe, that way will we goe.</hi> The fourth branch of <hi>Guile,</hi> is, the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a tolerable name vpon a groſſe ſinne, that ſo either it may not be ſeene, or may not appeare in it owne likenes. Thus in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16520:25"/> world drunkenneſſe is called, Goodfellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; Riotouſneſſe, Merie-meeting; Gaming, a paſſing of the Time; Couetouſneſſe, is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med warines; Cooſenage, the liuing by a mans witte, diſſembling, Policie. The vſurer will haue his practiſe called Intereſt, or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, or Putting out, any thing ſaue plaine vſury. Implacableneſſe is called Stoutneſſe; Fornication a ſtepping a little awry; ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, a fooliſh cuſtome; Pride by a milder name is called vanity; Ignorance is coloured with a pretence of ſimplicitie, and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedneſſe; Oppreſſion is ſaid to be the making the moſt of a mans owne. And thus in many other things, as in theſe, the Deuill beguileth vs, and teacheth vs to lie to our owne ſoules. The fift Branch, is, to deriue and tranſlate a ſinne committed by vs to another, thereby to eaſe our ſelues wholly, or at the leaſt by hauing a partner, that it may be the more light vpon our owne ſhoulder. So Adam be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing challenged by God for eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruite, ſought to deriue the fault, partly to God himſelfe, partly to his wife, <hi>The woman that thou gaueſt to be with me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhe gaue me of the Tree, &amp; I did eate.</hi> So <hi>Heuah</hi> likewiſe, it was her excuſe, <hi>The Serpent alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled me &amp; I did eat,</hi> thus you ſhal haue aſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſay ſometime for himſelfe, that he could not otherwiſe be beleeued: the riotous ſaith, Companie drew him in: the vſurer ſaith, he was importuned to lend, &amp; offered largely for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16520:26"/> the loane. So the Simoniacall both Patrone and Prelate, are at this day at variance, vpon which of the two, the ſinne of corruption ſhould lie. The one pleadeth the greedines of the Miniſtry that will offer ſo deepely: The other alleadgeth the hardnes and ſtraitnes of the Patrones, whome nothing but a gift in the Boſome can perſwade. This is alſo a ſpice of this <hi>Spirituall Guile.</hi> The ſixt Branch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is a wrong Reaſoning from the examples of the falles of Gods children, related in the Scripture. There is many a man who thus thinketh with himſelfe, <hi>was not Dauid an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulter? Did not Salomon keepe many concubines? Had not many of the Patriarches (who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding were well reported of) multiplicitie of Wiues? Was not Noah drunken? Did not Lot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit inceſt with his owne daughters? Did not Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter curſe and ſweare, and denie his Maſter? And therfore why ſhould I be afraid to ſatisfie my owne Luſtes, and to fulfill my owne deſires, and to follow my owne beſt pleaſing courſes? No doubt, it may be as well with me, as it was with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: By Repentance, they at laſt recouered, and ſo may I.</hi> Thus many a one ſecretly harteneth and encourageth himſelfe to continuance in Euill, by a falſe and vniuſt applying of the falles and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of Gods children. The only vſe whereof is, before we fal, to make vs watchfull, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in them Mans Infirmitie; and after we haue fallen, and are touched in conſcience, to put vs in hope of Gods mercie: and not to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16520:26"/> be (as it were) a ſtale, vnder the ſhadow whereof, we may the more boldly giue our ſelues ouer to vngodlineſſe. The ſeauenth Branch of this Guile is, a miſinterpreting of thoſe gracious teſtimonies, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath, of Gods forbearance, and milde dealing with his children, which belong to his Election. It is ſaid in holy Scripture, that <hi>God will ſpare his Elect, as a man ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerueth him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> that in them he will accept the Will for the deede, the Endeauour for the full performance; that he will paſſe by their Infirmities; that their ſinnes ſhall not ſeparate them from his loue; that he looketh rather to the truth of their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then to the quantitie of their Obedience. Theſe and the like aſſurances, the Scripture giueth of the Lords conniuence (as I may ſo ſpeake) and of his remitting the ſtraightnes of his Iuſtice towardes thoſe that are his; which things are indeede exceeding full of comfort to all thoſe which know rightly to applie them. But now, many wretched ones hearing this, doe euen coſen themſelues with a conceit, that their Heart is good, their Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the beſt, and their deſire to be as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the Pureſt: and ſo, becauſe God will (in his kindnes) accept good beginnings in his Elect, though the ſame be but weake, and like <hi>ſmoking Flaxe;</hi> therefore they imagine that, albeit their courſes of life are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſuch as in no reſpect, in regard of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16520:27"/> groſſe ſinnes can be iuſtified, yet with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe and proteſtation of a good Will and deſire, and endeauour, to bleare the Eyes of God, and to ſcape vnpuniſhed at the day of Reckoning. This is a Dangerous ſubtilty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an Abuſe of the riches of Gods mercie, and a turning of the ſweeteſt propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of his Nature, into wantonneſſe. The eight branch of this Guile is, a Miſtaking the nature of ſinne: as for example: Some man hauing ſome one groſſe ſinne, raigning in him, which (perhaps) is alſo in the world ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, as, whoredome, oppreſſion, ſwearing, &amp;c. thinketh with himſelfe, that though this be indeede a foule fault, yet it is his onely fault, and many times, he thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muneth with his owne Heart: <hi>True it is (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it) there is ſuch a groſſe ſinne which I am guilty of, and it may be the world ſeeth it, and it is ſome blemiſh and diſgrace vnto me: but what then? I hope when they haue named that, they haue named all: they can (I am ſure) lay no other matter to my charge, onely this excepted: and I know no man liueth without a fault, therefore I truſt I may be the better borne withall.</hi> This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt ariſeth (as I haue ſaid) vpon a miſtaking of the Nature of ſinne, men thinking, that ſinne may goe alone by it ſelfe without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie: as though a man could be giuen to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie onely, and to no other iniquitie: to oppreſſion onely, and to no other vice: to drunkennes onely, and to no other enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16520:27"/> It is vnpoſſible. Theſe groſſe ſinnes haue many attendants, and it cannot be, that they ſhould goe ſingle. Sinne is the ſicknes of the ſoule. As therefore in the diſeaſes of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, we ſee, that euery maine griefe, as the ſtone, gout, peſtilence, &amp;c. hath certaine infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour griefes annexed to it; ſo euery grand-ſinne, hath other petit euills to attend it, and to feede it (as it were) without which, it can neuer come to any great perfection. So that it is a plaine Errour, when a man perſwadeth himſelfe, This or this is my onely ſinne, not conſidering what a troupe and traine follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euery ſoule and open Euill. The ninth branch is, the drawing of a falſe concluſion out of the Lords long-ſuffering. It is that which Dauid mentioneth, when he bringeth in God thus ſpeaking to the Wicked man: <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done, and I held my to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.21.</note> 
                  <hi>therefore thou thoughteſt, I was like thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecc. 8.11.</note> And Salomon, <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an euil worke is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the Heart of the children of men, is fully ſet in them to doe euill.</hi> It is an ordinarie reaſoning among many, thus, Surely if God were ſo ſeuere, or ſo deepely diſpleaſed with my euill courſes, as it may ſeeme by ſome Texts of Scripture, and as ſome Preachers would perſwade, I doe not thinke he would ſo long haue forborne me, and (which is more maruailous) that he would haue thus heaped outward Things vpon me; therefore I ſee not to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16520:28"/> (vnleſſe I will be afraid of ſhadowes, and terrified with words) but that I may continue in my owne courſe, and ſeeke mine owne ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as heretofore I haue beene accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed. The tenth branch of this Guile is, a Hoping to ſatisfie, and make amends for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Euill courſes by ſome ſpeciall ſeruices &amp; deuotions, or by ſome ſhewes of charitie. This is firſt, the guilefull conceipt of all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts:<note place="margin">Annot. Rhem. Luc. 11. ſec. 5.</note> for ſo are our Rhemiſts owne words, in their notes, that Almes extinguiſh ſinne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme ſinne, make cleane and ſatisfie for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer offences, and are to be done as a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation to God for former euills. The ſame is their Opinion of faſtings, of penance, of pilgrimage, and the like. Secondly, this is the blinde Imagination of our ſottiſh ignorant people at this day, who (for want of better inſtruction) are frozen in the dregges of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, and ſuppoſe the due obſeruation of ſome ſolemne feſtiualls in the yeare, as they come in their courſe, to be a kind of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for a multitude of other defaults; and that if they be precize in the keeping of theſe, and the like rituous traditions, then they are very religious. Thirdly, this is alſo a deuiſe by which many worldly men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themſelues, who hauing by rapine and extortion, by gaping ouer the heads of the poore, by treading vpon them and grinding their faces, and by other the like violent and indirect courſes, raked much together, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16520:28"/> to remedie all this both with God and the world, by ſome largeſſe, and beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the poore, or to the Church at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe; and being poſſeſſed herewith, they run on, preſuming by this meanes to make a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſatisfaction, both to recouer their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with men, and to gaine fauour alſo with the Lord. The eleuenth and laſt branch of this <hi>Guile:</hi> is to looke no further then to a <hi>ſhew of Godlineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5.</note> and to thinke ones ſelfe religious inough, if he haue learned the Art of ſeeming, and can make an outward ſemblance of that, which indeede is farre, from their Hearts. Theſe which are thus minded, if the world hold a good opinion of them, they thinke themſelues to be very holy, if men can not chalenge them, they account themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable. This is right hypocriſie. Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, is a greeke word, and ſignifieth a ſtage-player, who many times, for the time weareth the habite, and carrieth the ſtile and title of a king, himſelfe beeing but a raſcall, or bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the part of ſome valourous knight, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man of no reſolution, or repreſenteth a chaſt and modeſt louer, when his owne life is a practiſe of vncleanes: This is properly an Hypocrite, and beeing applied to matters of religion, it ſignifieth ſuch an one, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and mouth, and face, and habite, make by fittes and vpon occaſions, great ſhewes of Pletie, when in his heart, he is nothing leſſe then he makes ſhew of. Yet, this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16520:29"/> Religion of the world, and from hence come ſo many courſes for getting of a man, a name, and opinion of religion. One man ſheweth himſelfe a ſharpe reprouer and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recter of the errors of others, that ſo he may be thought to be ſuch an one, who cannot brooke or ſuffer euill, and yet the ſame not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is ſlacke inough in reforming his owne corruptions; like to him of whom our Sauiour ſpeaketh in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Math. 7.3.4.</note> who forgetting the <hi>Beame</hi> in his owne Eie, was very deſirous, as might ſeeme, to caſt out the <hi>Mote,</hi> which was in his brothers Eie. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſome outward obſeruations will ſeeme very precize, which are but as it were the Circumſtances of religion, in the meane time neglecting the maine duties; after the faſhion of the Scribes &amp; Phariſies, to whom Chriſt denounced a woe becauſe they did <hi>tithe minte, and anyſe and cummin, and did leaue the waightier matter of the Law:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.23.</note> A third ſort to be thought religious, will not ſticke to giue ſome teſtimonie of reformation, and like Saul in his expedition againſt Amaleck, who killed the worſer ſtuffe, and ſaued the beſt of the ſpoile aliue, ſo they will kill (as might ſeeme) ſome petite ſins of leſſe profit advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, or delight, &amp; yet let the great ſinnes, the crucifying wherof ſhould chieflly teſtify ther obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.20.</note>) bleate &amp; cry ſtil in the eares of the moſt high. Thus Herod, reformed ſom things at Iohns preaching, but the gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſin he would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16520:29"/> by no meanes be perſwaded to reforme, but thought the preacher might better ſpare his head, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he could liue without that ſinn; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch Herods there are now adaies, who, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a godly reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is vrged, cry with the ſame wordes, though I feare me not with the ſame mind,<note place="margin">2. King. 5.18.</note> that that good Syrian vſed <hi>Onely herein the Lord be mercifull vnto vs,</hi> let vs be born with in this, &amp; beſides it we will me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing. As me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s courſes are many, for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of an Opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo their endes are diuerstone ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth it for his profit; as the <hi>Shechemites</hi> yeelded to be circumciſed vpon this hope, <hi>Shall not their flockes, and cattell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 34.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and all their ſubſtance he ours?</hi> Another doth it for his credit and eſtimation. So, <hi>Saul</hi> though he did not much loue or eſteeme Samuel, as a Prophet, yet when Samuel in ſome diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment was departing from him, he impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned him to ſtay with him, and this was his reaſon, <hi>Honour me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 15.30.</note> 
                  <hi>I pray thee before the Elders of my people.</hi> He though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Samuels preſence would grace him, otherwiſe it is likely he did not much regard him. And I doe verily thinke, this to haue beene one cauſe, which mooued Herod at the firſt, to countenance Iohn Baptiſt: becauſe, the people accounting Iohn as a Prophet, it could not but make much for Herods credit to be a protection vnto him. Another yet maketh Religion, but as a cloke to greater vilanies: ſo Iezabel pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing by falſe witneſſes to take away Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16520:30"/> life,<note place="margin">1. King. 21.9.</note> yet would grace the matter with proclaiming a Faſt. And Abſolom made the performance of a Vow in Hebron,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.7.</note> to be the ſhadow of his vnnaturall conſpiracie againſt his father. This is the laſt Branch of this <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Guile;</hi> the ſumme of It, is this, when for matters of Religion men content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the Iudgement of the world, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelues very holy, if the world ſo account them. Thus haue I ripped vp Adams fig-leaues, and ſhewed you, as I thinke, all the particulars of this <hi>Spirituall Guile;</hi> whereby men thinking to deceiue God, doe at the laſt vtterly beguile their owne ſoules. I haue beene longer in it then I thought; but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and neceſſitie of the point, hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercaried me. Now, <hi>Truth</hi> is in euery reſpect contrarie hereunto, as full of plain-nes, as this is full of ſubtiltie, making a man as like to the God of <hi>Truth,</hi> as the other maketh him to reſemble the <hi>father of lies.</hi> It is briefely this; An humble and feeling acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a mans naturall ſinnefulneſſe; an ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauating to the conſcience of euery euill, when a man hath to doe directly with the Lord; a ſhunning and auoiding of all ſhifts, either of pretenſed examples, or of Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or of ſhrouding great ſinnes vnder to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable names, or of tranſlating faults vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or of preſuming vpon Gods goodnes, or of hoping by petit meanes to redeeme of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, or by couering a falſe heart with a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16520:30"/> face and vizard of Religion. This is <hi>Truth in the inward parts,</hi> as Dauid tearmeth it. This was in Hezekiah, <hi>O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.16. Iſay. 38.3.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue walked before thee in Truth.</hi> And from hence ſpringeth <hi>Truth</hi> in the conſcience, giuing a true infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of peace wrought with God by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and aſſuring a man by the <hi>Truth</hi> of his Obedience, of the <hi>Truth</hi> of his Faith: <hi>Truth</hi> in the mouth, to put away Lying,<note place="margin">Eph 4.25.</note> and all manner ſpeaches, which may giue the Lie to a good profeſſion. <hi>Truth</hi> in the Eies, not to <hi>behold Vanity:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Truth</hi> in the eare not <hi>to heare the Inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cauſeth to erre,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 19.27.</note> 
                  <hi>from the words of knowledge: Truth</hi> in the Hand, in reſpect of the vprightneſſe, and fidelitie, and plaine-nes, and open-nes of a mans dealing among men. Thus I haue ſhewed you, the nature of this <hi>Truth,</hi> which is comprehended in one clauſe thus, <hi>True Obedience to that which a man knoweth to be the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next point, is to ſhew the neceſſitie of this kind of <hi>Truth,</hi> or namely <hi>Truth</hi> of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or Obedience to the <hi>Truth.</hi> The neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, may be gathered by that which ſcripture hath deliuered of it, all whoſe Precepts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a neceſſitie.<note place="margin">Pro. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When wiſedome entreth into thy Heart and knowledge delighteth thy ſoule, Then ſhall counſell preſerue thee, and vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing keepe thee.</hi> So that there is no benefite by knowledge, till it come into the heart, &amp; hath wrought upon the Affections. Saint Iames ſpeaking of a generall apprehenſion of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16520:31"/> 
                  <hi>Truth</hi> of Religion,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> without vſe, ſaith, <hi>The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills</hi> haue it <hi>and doe tremble. Many ſhall come in that day, and ſhal ſay vnto me Lord, Lord, we haue prophecied in thy name</hi> (let vs which are prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers conſider it,) yet Chriſt ſhall ſay vnto them,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from me, ye that worke iniquitie.</hi> Here is knowledge,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.17.</note> and yet no ſaluation. <hi>If you know theſe things,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt elſe where) <hi>bleſſed are you, if you doe them:</hi> It is the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which maketh vp the Happineſſe. <hi>To euery one that is thirſtie, Come buy:</hi> and what then? Eate to: the Hauing is nothing, without the vſing. Places of Scripture of this nature are infinite, all which doe confirme thus much; that the Purchaſers of the <hi>Truth,</hi> ought not to be like, the Rich, (but yet miſerable) purchaſers of the world, who, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue gotten much into their hands, yet goe as neere the winde, fare as hardly, toyle as pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, looke as rufully, as they did when they had nothing, and ſo (as Salomon ſaith,) <hi>make themſelues poore hauing wealth:</hi> Such muſt not the Buyers of the <hi>Truth</hi> be,<note place="margin">Pro. 13.7.</note> knowing much, doing little, hauing (as it were) golden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and leaden Affections; And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede to haue recourſe vnto the true defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Lie, there is no more proper Lie, then when a man knoweth one thing, and doth the cleane contrarie:<note place="margin">Montiri eſt contra men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temire.</note> To lie, is, to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a mans minde. So that when a mans carriage giueth his knowledge the Lie, that man is, though he know the <hi>Truth,</hi> a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16520:31"/> Lyer before God. So much briefly for the neceſſitie of this <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Now to apply this (which is the third point I vndertooke) this is the vſe of that, which hath beene ſaid; euen to ſtirre vs vp (as before to ſoundnes of knowledge in the <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo now) to heartie and vnfained Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience therevnto: that as by following the former Exhortation we ſhall be able to ſay; <hi>Thus we haue laboured, thus we abound in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, thus are we grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in Religion;</hi> ſo by this,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note> I mean by this Obeying <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Hart the Form of Doctrine</hi> which we haue learned, we may with ſeeking vſe the wordes of Ieremie,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.24.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is my portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith my ſoule:</hi> and of Dauid, <hi>I haue ſworne and will performe it, that I will keepe thy righteous iudgements.</hi> So that when we ſhal heare the Lord ſay in his word,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 106.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them to feare me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 5.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and to keepe all my commandements alwaies;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119 5.</note> our hearts within vs, may make Anſwere, <hi>Oh that our waies were directed to keepe thy ſtatutes.</hi> This is the life of all Religion,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5.</note> this is the <hi>Power of Godlines,</hi> namely,<note place="margin">Pſal. 233.</note> when as the <hi>Truth</hi> ſeated in the vnderſtanding like the oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which being powred on Aarons head ranne down to his Beard, and went euen to the skirtes of his garments, ſo this, deriueth it ſelfe into the whole man, and ſweeteneth all his Actions, making him to giue vp his <hi>Body, a liuing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, holy and acceptable vnto God.</hi> And ſurely,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> if I had the beſt gift in perſwading which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16520:32"/> God hath giuen to any man, and could make my wordes <hi>like nailes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl 12 11.</note> 
                  <hi>faſtened by the Maſters of the Aſſemblies,</hi> I could not beſtow my skill better, then in vrging, and preſſing this dutie: and that in theſe three reſpects. Firſt, becauſe of the difficultie of the dutie. It is by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees eaſier, to become a man of deepe iudgement, then of a religious Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: a harder matter to rectifie the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then to informe the vnderſtanding. And there is good reaſon for it, even in nature: In a matter of Knowledge, to be apprehended by the vnderſtanding part of Man, there may ſuch forcible reaſons and neceſſarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences be drawne, wherevnto it cannot poſſibly but giue conſent: In the affections it is not ſo. For, that which mooueth them, is ſome ſenſible, either profitte or delight, which becauſe it is not ſo eaſily felt, and ſo ſoone perceiued in the caſe of Obedience, &amp; reformation, therefore it is an eaſie matter, for the vnderſtanding to be well enlightened in the knowledge of religion, and yet the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to remaine cold and lumpiſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any loue to religion. So that a man may ſooner runne through the whole Circle of Knowledge, then ſet one ſteppe forward to Obedience. Now in reaſon, that which is ſo hard in performing, requireth vehemencie of perſwading. The ſecond reſpect, why I hold it ſo worthy the paines of me, or of any other to vrge this duty, is the excellencie of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16520:32"/> it; and that apppeareth hereby, becauſe the left graine of Obedience, doth as it were ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the whole lumpe of knowledge: the ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt quantitie of heartie affections, is the meaſure of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: God, reſpecteth not how much, but how heartily: yea, if a man be cut ſhort of the fulneſſe of obedience, yet, if he haue an vnfeined deſire, he is accepted <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he hath:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12.</note> ſo precious a thing is the heartie Embracing of this Truth. The third reſpect, is the generall want hereof among the men of this generation. For, as we haue cauſed the enemies of God to blaſphemie, I meane Papiſts, and to ſpeake euill of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſion, becauſe of our fruit-leſnes; ſo it would make the <hi>Eies</hi> of Dauid to <hi>guſh out with riuers of waters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.136. 2. Pet. 2.8.</note> and <hi>vexe the righteous ſoule</hi> of Lot, if they liued among vs; to ſee firſt, how the more learned and wiſer ſort, (who yet would be thought Religious) make religion onely a matter of contemplation, &amp; thinke it inough to be able to diſcourſe in matters of Diuinity, as in other things vpon occaſion; and then next, how the common ſort, (that are yet called Chriſtians,) be as far from the power and truth of Religion, as they which neuer heard of Religion. So then, this being a dutie of that difficultie, of that excellencie, of that neceſſitie, (that I may at laſt end this firſt part) ſuffer me to renue the former exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one word: As you muſt ſpare no coſt to poſſeſſe the <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16520:33"/> muſt euen giue all, euen for one little <hi>Modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> of heartie obedience to the <hi>Truth.</hi> For the purchaſing wherof, I know no other place to remit thee vnto, then that which I named for the purchaſing of knowledg, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of the Lord, the Houſe of God, where his word is moſt faithfully diſpenſed: where the faithfull Steward of Gods houſe, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to diſtribute to euery man his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in due ſeaſon, will, as he doth prooue the Doctrine, to ſtabliſh thy Iudgement, ſo apply it alſo, and make vſe of it to direct thy Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And thus much for the firſt part of the Text,<note place="margin">The ſecond part of the Text.</note> the Iniunction, <hi>Buy the Truth.</hi> Now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the Inhibition, <hi>ſell not the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not neede to ſpend much time, in ſearching out the meaning of this clauſe. For firſt, the word <hi>Truth</hi> is ſo to be vnderſtood here as in the former part. And then, what it is to <hi>ſell the Truth,</hi> wil eaſily be gathered from the conſideration of <hi>Buying,</hi> which hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto beene expounded. As then Salomon when he enioyned the <hi>Buying</hi> of the <hi>Truth,</hi> meant thereby a carefull and an Induſtrious endeauouring to obtain the <hi>Truth;</hi> ſo here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the <hi>ſale of Truth,</hi> he inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to forgoe the <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The only diuiſion which I will vſe, ſhall be to apply this <hi>ſelling,</hi> to the double Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word <hi>Truth:</hi> So that I haue here two points to handle: 1. <hi>Sell not the knowledge of the Truth:</hi> 2, <hi>Forgoe not, part not with thy Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16520:33"/> to the Truth.</hi> Of theſe two in order. And firſt of this, <hi>ſell not the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> that is, Be not wrought by any meanes, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy Iudgement when thou art once grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſetled in the <hi>Truth.</hi> Now as in han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling of the former part, I did apply the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of <hi>Buying,</hi> ſo in this alſo, I muſt haue leaue, to follow the phraſe of <hi>ſelling,</hi> ſo farre forth, as (agreeably to the Rule &amp; Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith,) it may giue light vnto this place.</p>
               <p>Of a good and thriftie Husband, which is reſolued not to part with that, which by his great Induſtry and charge he hath gotten, two things are required. 1. To continue and preſerue his eſtate. 2. By all honeſt meanes to encreaſe it. He which hath a reſolution not to ſell that, which he hath, you know he will haue nought to doe, with common Brokers, ſuch as are lifting (as it were) at euery Thing, and lie in the wind to catch whatſoeuer, any vnthrift ſhall be willing to depart with; or els, if he happen to haue to doe with ſuch, he wil bewiſe to know how torid his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to keepe that which he hath from their fingering. This is wordly Pollicie; not much vnlike to this, ought to be the wiſedome of euery good Chriſtian in this behalfe. As our Times are, Sathan, (who is the captaine Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and cannot abide this Chriſtian frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) hath two principall agents, who follow his cauſes, and are dealers for him in this kind. 1. The Atheiſt. 2. The Papiſt. Againſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16520:34"/> both theſe, he which is a right religious <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> and crieth, God forbid that I ſhould part with the poſſeſſion of Gods <hi>Truth,</hi> muſt arme himſelfe. Firſt, for the Atheiſt, (who is in the Deuills hand, as the ſword was in the hand of Ioab toward Amaſa, to ſtrike Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Heart, that he may not need to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his ſtroke; the beſt courſe in regard of him, is altogither to diſclaime him, &amp; not ſo much as to vſe any ſpeaches of chafering with him; but as Saint Iames ſpeaketh touching the Deuill, at the very firſt Encounter <hi>to reſiſt him.</hi> For,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.7.</note> it is a dangerous thing, in religion, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the principall pointes, as of the Godhead, the Immortality of the ſoule, the Reſurrection, and the like, to admitte of any diſcourſe, although it may be pretended to be but for conference ſake, whereby the <hi>Truth</hi> of theſe Things might be called into Queſtion. Reaſon teacheth vs, that euery Arte muſt haue his principles, which muſt not be gainſaid. I remember what the Philoſopher could ſay; If any ſhould diſpute and argue touching this Principle, whether there be Motion in nature, let him be beaten, till he confeſſe, that he who ſtriketh him, may deſiſt from beating him; or, whether the fire be hotte, let him be made to feele it; and ſo, he that ſhould call the Immortalitie of the ſoule into queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; it were pitie but he ſhould be ſerued, as he did voluntarily do to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who threw himſelfe headlong from a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16520:34"/> Rocke that he might experimentally know it. The Heatheniſh Epheſians were wiſer: for, when they heard Paul beginne to call the Godhead of Diana into doubt,<note place="margin">Act. 19.34.</note> they carried it away with a ſhoute, <hi>Great is Diana of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> they thought it a thing not to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured. And through this Flood-gate, came this Sea of miſery into the world in which we are all ouerwhelmed, euen, that our gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother <hi>Heuah,</hi> did entertaine a diſcourſe, &amp; Parley with Sathan,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> touching the <hi>Truth</hi> of Gods word: As indeed, to what end are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and reaſonings of this nature? For,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.32.</note> 
                  <hi>If men will not beleeue Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> nothing can perſwade them. Furthermore: becauſe euery Man ſhall now &amp; then feele a little peice of an Atheiſt in his owne boſome (for each man by nature is that <hi>Foole</hi> which <hi>ſaith in his Heart, there is no God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note>) therefore (becauſe alſo the Principles of Atheiſme are grounded vpon Mans Reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,) it is good to be ſetled in this Rule; that the Myſteries of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion are not to be examined by Humane Reaſon. For which cauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The naturall man perceiueth not the Things of the ſpirit of God for they are Fooliſhnes vnto him, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>The Wiſedome of the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> 
                  <hi>is Enmitie againſt God</hi> and, <hi>If any man among you ſeeme to be wiſe in this world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.18</note> 
                  <hi>let him be a Foole that he may be wiſe.</hi> It is not in Religion, as in naturall Things: In them, a Iudgement is grounded vpon Experience and obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16520:35"/> and the Induction of many particulars, from which is drawne a generall concluſion: In di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, the very Thing deliuered by Scripture is to be acknowledged, though it be not as yet ſtrengthened by Experience, <hi>Bleſſed are they that haue not ſeene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.19. Heb 11.1. Ioh. 6.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and haue beleeued, ſaith our Sauiour, and Faith is the Euidence of things which are not ſeene, and, we haue beleeued, and knowne, &amp;c.</hi> ſaid the Diſciples. As Abraham hoped againſt Hope, ſo a Religious man muſt beleeue againſt all carnall Reaſon to beleeue. And indeed, if wee will tie our ſelues to Reaſon, there can be no ſoundnes in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: For bring your maine pointes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to Reaſons Barre, there to receiue their Triall, and what ſhall be the verdict but this; that the doctrine of the Trinitie is ſenſleſſe, of the Incarnation of Chriſt, abſurd; of the reſurrection, incredible; of the vnion of Chriſts two natures, vnlikely; of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, vnpoſſible; of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Vniuſt; of Preaching, Fooliſhnes, and ſo of others: howbeit I hold this alſo, that where Scripture approoueth Reaſon, there Reaſon may be brought in as a witnes, although neuer as iudge; as in the caſe of the Reall preſence, the Scripture aſcribing to Chriſt a naturall Body, maketh naturall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon an argument ſtrong inough, againſt ſuch an vnreaſonable Opinion. Thus if a man ſhall bring his owne thoughts into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie, which exalt themſelues againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:16520:35"/> knowledge of God, he ſhall be reaſonably well garded againſt the Atheiſt, and maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this ſpirituall poſſeſſion of Gods <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond Manager of Sathans Buſines, in ſeeking to draw vs to an vnthriftie ſelling of the <hi>Truth,</hi> is the Papiſt, who was neuer buſier, nor fuller of deuiſes then he is at this day, labouring by Bookes, by privie Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by Bribes, and by all meanes which hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh witte can deviſe, to draw men from the acknowledgement and profeſſion of Gods <hi>Truth.</hi> Their common motiues, are well knowne to thoſe, which know any thing, and how they ſeeke to blind and dazell the Eies of many with the glorious (but yet preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) ſhewes of Antiquitie, vniuerſalitie, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Lineall ſucceſſion, Catholique Church, Church planted by the Apoſtles, Fathers, Counſells, Miracles, and the like. Now to ſhew the weakenes of every of theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, the falſehood of ſome, the pretenſing of other ſome, the Inuailidity of them all, were a long peice of worke, and not poſſibly to be (though it were but ſlightly,) ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, in this ſhortnes of Time: yet leſt I ſhould ſeeme to name an enemie, &amp; to giue no directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him, therfore, that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meaneſt chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, who hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome comfortable know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>truth,</hi> may know how to keep his Right againſt euery inueigling and catching Papiſt, I will deliuer theſe two inſtructions.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16520:36"/> The firſt is, the ſpeech of the Apoſtle to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Continue thou in the Things, which thou haſt learned, and art perſwaded thereof, knowing of whom thou haſt learned them.</hi> I pray you to conſider the Place and you ſhall find it a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Preſeruatiue, and as good as a grimme Porter to keepe out thoſe Popiſh factors that would defeat vs of our inheritance. The Apoſtle preſſeth a ſtiffe, and firme continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in <hi>Truth</hi> receiued, when as theſe two Things concurre with it: 1. A mans own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion: 2. The conſideration of the Quality of thoſe which firſt taught vs. Firſt, for a mans owne Perſwaſion; marke I pray you, leaſt I ſhould ſeeme, in ſteed of grounded ſetlednes, to commend ſelfe-willed Peeuiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: By beeing <hi>perſwaded,</hi> Paul meaneth thus much, as if he had ſaid to Timothie: <hi>If it be an opinion, which thou haſt not ſuddenly entertained, but vpon good Aduiſe; if it hath ſeated it ſelfe in thy iudgement, then when as thou with Care and Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with Humility, with vſing the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie meanes, with Praier vnto God, with heartie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be guided into Truth, enquiredſt after know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſurely thou oughteſt not (beeing by theſe degrees brought to it and in this manner perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in it) raſhly and ſuddenly to forgoe it.</hi> This is ment by Perſwaſion in this place; <hi>A ſetlednes of Iudgement, following vpon an orderly courſe to bring a man therevnto.</hi> The ſecond thing which muſt concurre, is <hi>Conſider and marke of whom thou haſt learned them: that is, Obſerue, &amp;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16520:36"/> note well, what kind of men they are, by whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry thou haſt beene inſtructed, If they be men, who by their Fidelitie in Teaching, and by the bleſſing of God vpon their Labours, in vſing their Miniſtry to convert mens ſoules, doe carie with them the ſeale of their Miniſtrie, nay, if thine own ſoule can witnes for them either of theſe, out of thine owne feeling, then beware of a Doctrine contrary to that thou haſt beene Taught; though I would not haue thee tie thy ſelfe to any mans Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, yet be not raſh, be well adviſed, before thou alter thy iudgement confirmed by ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</hi> This is the firſt thing which I will in the Lord commend as a direction, for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort, (who cannot enter into the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of every ſeuerall) to preſerue them from the allurements of Poperie, and from <hi>ſelling</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> to euery cheating compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing which I will commend vnto the ſimpler ſort, as a meanes to keepe them, from being entangled, with the large offers of ſubtill Papiſts, which ſeeke to draw men from the <hi>Truth,</hi> is this; when they ſhall be perſwaded to any point, of Poperie, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the doctrine taught amongſt vs at this day, either by writing, or privie ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, or corrupt and vnſound Teaching, let them compare it with the contrarie which we hold, and well ponder with themſelues, (deſiring alſo the aſſiſtance of Gods ſpirit) which of the two Opinions, maketh moſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16520:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:16520:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:16520:38"/> for the Glorie of God, for the comfort of a diſtreſſed and diſtracted conſcience, and for the reſtraint of the Libertie of the fleſh: and which ſoeuer of the two, they ſhall find, by the witnes of their owne conſcience, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with the voice of the Scripture) to make moſt for all, or for any of theſe three, let them take that, to be the ſoundeſt, and for their life not dare to renounce it. Marke the Reaſon. Firſt the End why God made all things, was the <hi>Glory</hi> of his own name: the end why he redeemed mankind was, <hi>That no fleſh ſhould reioice in his preſence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 16.4. 1. Cor. 1.30.31.</note> 
                  <hi>but that he which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth ſhould reioyce in the Lord;</hi> that no man ſhould haue cauſe to thanke himſelfe, but ſhould be compelled to aſcribe all vnto the Lord. By this Rule Paul decideth the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie touching Iuſtification by Faith and workes; <hi>where is then the reioycing?</hi> ſaith he) <hi>It is excluded:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.27.</note> By what law;</hi> (that is, <hi>By what means of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) of workes? Nay, but by the Law of Faith.</hi> Faith taketh all from man, and aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth all to the Lord:<note place="margin">verſ. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore we conclude, that a man is iuſtified by faith without the workes of the law.</hi> So that hence I confirme This Rule, that looke which point of Doctrine doth moſt debaſe man, and giue the whole glorie of all good vnto the Lord, that is the <hi>Truth,</hi> and that is alone to be embraced. For the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Rule, which is touching comfort: Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom 15.4.</note> that the Ende why the Scripture was written was for our <hi>Learning and comfort:</hi> The
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16520:38"/> Ende of all, both writing and Teaching is, that man feeling the extremitie of his owne miſerie, might notwithſtanding be ſetled in the comfortable aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus. So then, that doctrine which affordeth the ſoundeſt comfort, then, when a wounded conſcience moſt deſireth comfort, that is the Truth, and that is not at any hand to be forſaken. Thirdly, touching the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the fleſh, I remember the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye haue beene called into libertie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> 
                  <hi>onely vſe not year libertie as an occaſion to the fleſh:</hi> as who would ſay, The doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, though it be a doctrine of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to the Spirit, freeing it from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of ſinne and Sathan, yet it is a doctrine of Reſtraint to the Fleſh; ſo that when you feele the Fleſh begin to breake out, and take libertie, then know it to be an Abuſe of the Doctrine of Libertie. This was Pauls mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. So that it is an vnfallible Canon, that that Doctrine which preſſeth vpon men, the moſt preciſe and ſtrict Obedience to Gods will, not giuing any the leaſt toleration to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the ſmalleſt ſinne, but is ſtill curbing mans naturall inclination vnto Euill, that ſame is the <hi>Truth</hi> of God, that ought euery ſeruant of God to maintaine. I pray you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this Direction. I doe not for mine owne part (and I ſpeake it hauing often and aduiſedly thought vpon it) know any maine point of Popetie, but it may well be tried by
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16520:39"/> theſe Rules. So that you ſhall finde all the Grounds of that Religion, either to obſcure Gods glorie, or to weaken mans comfort, or (what pretenſe ſoeuer it may make,<note place="margin">Col 2.23.</note> by not ſeeming <hi>to ſpare the Bodie</hi>) to giue libertie to the fleſh. I pray you trie the Truth hereof vpon occaſion, and then credit the Direction accordingly.</p>
               <p>Thus much briefly how a Chriſtian good husband, who hauing at a deare hand pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the <hi>Truth,</hi> and is willing ſtill to enioy it, may keepe the ſame from all Huckſters, whether they be ſuch as would draw him to No Religion, or ſuch as would winne him to a falſe religion. A needefull point in theſe decaying times, in which Sathan knowing that <hi>he hath but a ſhort time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>hath great wrath,</hi> and beſtirreth himſelfe exceedingly; and in which alſo, many, as it were wearie of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, of the ſyncere doctrine of the Goſpel, doe long for the fleſh-pots of Egypt, for the groſſenes of Poperie; others goe about to make a Medley of Poperie and true Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to put the Arke and Dagon into one Temple, which cannot be, others conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the courſe of Times, carrie themſelues in a kinde of Indifferencie, caſting (like the wiſe Steward) what they ſhall doe hereafter. So that if euer the Papiſts, leauing all other perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſhould haue opportunitie (which God forbid) to reſume their old Argument, <hi>From the clubbes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> threatning vs, that, If we will
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16520:39"/> 
                  <hi>not ſell our Inheritance,</hi> they will fire vs out, it is much to be feared, that a great many of vs would reſigne our intereſt, chooſing rather to goe ſeeke a new, then to hold our old poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion vpon ſo hard conditions. I beſeech you therefore, let vs as well remember to take heed of a Thriftleſſenes in forſaking the <hi>Truth,</hi> as of Miſerablenes and Niggardice in purchaſing the <hi>Truth,</hi> and let me conclude this place, and exhortation, with the wordes of the Apoſtle; you that are, or hereafter by the bleſſing of God vpon the vſe of the good meanes, ſhall be grounded in Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Truth ſtand faſt, and keepe the Inſtructions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye haue beene taught; and I pray Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, who hath given vs Euerlaſting Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation &amp; good hope through grace, comfort our Heartes, and ſtabliſh vs, in euery word and good worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next point, is to vrge this Inhibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in regard of the <hi>Truth</hi> of Obedience; of which alſo this place is to be vnderſtood, which ſaith, <hi>ſell not the Truth,</hi> that is, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou art once entred into a holy courſe of true Obedience, ſee thou neuer forſake the ſame.</hi> For the well handling of this point, the moſt full and profitable courſe were this. In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as Sathan, the Arch-enemie of our ſoules, knowing, that the further we goe on in true Obedience, the further we are from his iuriſdiction, doth therefore, not faile to ſollicite vs, and by many ſeuerall meanes to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16520:40"/> be ever tempering with vs, to ſlake our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes, and to kill and coole all zeale with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs; for this cauſe it were good to diſcouer his plots, to deſigne his inſtruments, and to note the ſeuerall ſuggeſtions by which he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempteth to make vs caſt off all holy Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods <hi>Truth.</hi> Sometimes Profite hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, ſometime Pleaſure miſleadeth, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a feare to impaire our credit in the world is a ſtoppe, ſometimes a conceipt of too much ſtraitnes and difficultie in Religion diſcourageth, ſometimes an opinion that to much zeale is ſuperfluous, croſſeth vs; ſo that it is a hard matter, to play the good Husband in holding faſt a good profeſſion to the End. But, becauſe to enter into everie of theſe particulars, would require a more large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, therefore as a generall preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, againſt all occaſions that may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, I will onely commend, and confirme vnto you this Doctrine, namely; <hi>That he which hath entred into a good courſe of true obedience, ought not at any hand to deſiſt and fall away from the ſame.</hi> The courſe of Chriſtianitie, is often in Scripture compared to a Race, in which it ſufficeth not a man, either to haue run long, or to haue runne painefully, vnleſſe he hold out vnto the marke; nay, he which breaketh off, in the mid way, is as far from a reward as he which neuer ſet one ſteppe forward ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto; So in this Caſe, it booteth not a man, to haue beene ſometimes very forward, and to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16520:40"/> haue made ſome ſhew of loue and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto Gods <hi>Truth,</hi> vnleſſe he doe perſiſt, and continue therein vnto the end. Therefore, So runne (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that you may obtaine. ſo runne;</hi> that is, moderately in the beginning,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor 9.24.</note> conſtantly in the midſt, and cheerefully in the end, making the end rather better, then worſe then the Beginning. An vnſtayed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and fickle diſpoſition, to be caried with a humour, and to embrace a thing but for a fitte, is a thing ſo diſgracefull euen in common reaſon, that many men oftentimes doe perſiſt in that which is naught, rather to incurre the ſuſpition of vnſetlednes; much more, is it ſhamefull in matters of religion. And therefore, as it is the Brand of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to be like a whirlewind,<note place="margin">Pro 10.25.</note> ſo it is the note of the Righteous to be as an <hi>Euerlaſting Fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> All the promiſes of Happines in holy Scripture, are made with Condition of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. <hi>He that endureth to the end ſhall be ſaued; To him that ouer commeth will I giue, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.13. Reu. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Be faithfull to the Death, and thou ſhalt receiue the crowne of life.</hi> So that if you take away continuance, all hope of happines is vtterly overthrowne. In a word, not to ſay ſo much as might be ſpoken in this caſe; they which haue beene zealous, and carefull, &amp; forward, and doe after grow cold, their caſe is worſe, and their puniſhment more heauy. Firſt their caſe is worſe, becauſe hereby they are brought into the way, to that vnpardonable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16520:41"/> ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, ſo that if euer they recouer, it will coſt them the ſetting on. Againe their puniſhment is more heauie: For <hi>they</hi> who <hi>haue eſcaped from the filthines of the World, through the knowledge of the Lord &amp;c.</hi> If they be <hi>tangled againe therein, the latter end is worſe then the beginning.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> There is a neceſſarie vſe to be made of this point: Backſliding, falling away, looſing the firſt loue, are the common ſinnes of the profeſſors of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this age.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.10</note> The Church is ful of <hi>Demaſſes</hi> who haue left their old zeale and haue <hi>embraced the preſent world.</hi> The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed continuance of our happy Peace, hath beene to many an occaſion of Falling: It is time that the Lord ſhould quicken vs by ſome ſharper courſes. There be many, of whom it may be ſaid, <hi>He was a zealous Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, carefull in the waies of godlines: I knew ſuch an one, an earneſt and painefull preacher, ſtudious, induſtrious, of excellent giftes: There is an other, was pretily come on, and gaue good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Gods graces to be in him, was a diligent hearer, a man who loued to conferre of good Things; But now there is a great alteration, the world hath choked them, the Vanitie of outward things hath beguiled them and they are not the men they haue beene.</hi> Alas that any man ſhould giue occaſion to haue it ſo ſaid of him. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the ſaying, <hi>It is the moſt woefull thing to haue beene happy:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Miſerrimum eſt fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um.</note> and ſo, it is a miſerable thing to haue beene zealous, and now not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16520:41"/> to be zealous, to haue had Lands, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and large poſſeſſions, and now to be a begger, to haue had the <hi>Truth</hi> of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in poſſeſſion, but now to haue cleane parted therewithal. I beſeech you, if any here be guilty herein (as euery man, hath good cauſe to be ielous ouer himſelfe with a godly ielouſie) let him be admoniſhed to looke to it quickly, to <hi>repent and doe his firſt workes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> leaſt he incurre a double condemnation. Who will pitie him, that had land and liuing, and could not keepe it? and how ſhall the Lord be mercifull vnto him, who hauing knowne the <hi>Way of Truth</hi> ſhall <hi>turne from the holy Commandement giuen vnto him?</hi> And for others, which are (perhaps) but yet commers on and beginners in good things, as you ſhal learne, other Things, ſo learne this withall, that we haue need to keepe a narrow watch over our hartes,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ 3.13</note> leaſt we waxe wearie <hi>of well Doing,</hi> leaſt at vnawares a kind of ſacietie &amp; fulnes creepe vpon vs. To, beginne a thing is pleaſant, therefore for varieties ſake, many will beginne, but vpon ſome occaſions ſoone leaue off; ſo that all the proofe is in the End.</p>
               <p>There is one point more behinde, no leſſe neceſſarie then the former, a Branch of my diuiſion, and incident alſo to my Text; and that is, a Godly <hi>care to enlarge, and encreaſe the Truth which we haue purchaſed.</hi> In this fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and Thriuing Age, he is, among worldly wiſe men, halfe accounted an vnthrift, not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16520:42"/> onely, that maketh away his eſtate, either in whole, or in part, but alſo which doth not by his induſtrie, and prouidence ſomething bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame. And I pray you, mark, if my Text, doe not require ſo much: It is in the nature of euery Inhibition, or forbidding Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to imply the contrarie: As, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> comprehendeth this vnder it, <hi>Thou ſhalt by all honeſt meanes preſerue the life of thy neighbour:</hi> ſo, <hi>thou ſhalt not ſell the Truth:</hi> what muſt I then doe, (wilt thou ſay:) Thou muſt husband it well, and labour to encreaſe it. So that my Text very naturally, without ſetting it vpon the racke, occaſioneth the vrging of that dutie which the Scripture often doth perſwade, namely, <hi>A caring and endeauouring to thriue in Religion, to encreaſe both in knowledge and in obedience.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.18.</note> S. Peter giueth a charge, <hi>Grow in grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> Paul beſeecheth his hearers <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe more and more.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 4.18.</note> Salomon compareth the ſtate of a Chriſtian <hi>to the light, which ſhineth more and more vnto the perſit day.</hi> In Ezekiel, the graces of Gods ſpirit, are figured by the waters,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> iſſuing out of the Sanctuarie, which were firſt to the <hi>ankles,</hi> then to the <hi>knees,</hi> then to the <hi>Ioynes,</hi> then to a <hi>riuer that could not be paſſed ouer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 92 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Dauid calleth Gods ſeruants <hi>Trees, which bring forth fruit in their age,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then are fat,<note place="margin">Math. 25.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and flouriſhing.</hi> Chriſt in the Parable reporteth that the Euill ſeruant, though he kept the Talent in a napkin ſafe, yet was condemned for not encreaſing it.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16520:42"/> Thus you ſee the Truth of this Doctrine. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> And I pray you let vs make the vſe of it, to be ſtirred vp by it (ſo many as haue gotten ſome knowledge, and ſhewed ſome fruits of Obedience,) not to reſt ſatisfied therewith, thinking that we know enough, &amp; haue done enough, but after the worthie example of Paul, let vs ſtill <hi>forget that which is behinde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.13.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting that whereto we are come, to be ſcarſe worth the naming, and ſtriuing to goe from grace to grace, from vertue to vertue,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.7. Rom. 12.3.</note> 
                  <hi>from ſtrength to ſtrength, according as God hath dealt to euery one the meaſure of faith.</hi> Fleſh and blood is readie ſoone to ſatisfie it ſelfe, with a little in theſe things, though in other things it be vnſatiable; and worldly men (that would be thought religious for all that) they plead, <hi>All is well, and how Religious would you haue vs to be? Doe we not thus and thus, and what would you haue of vs more?</hi> To helpe this, I pray you remember this; He is the beſt Chriſtian, who is euer complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to himſelfe of his owne ſlacknes, and carieth a kind of holy Indignation againſt himſelfe, that he knoweth no more, and is no more obedient,<note place="margin">Phil 3.13.</note> more grieuing at that which is <hi>Behind,</hi> then pleaſing himſelfe in that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he is attained. And on the other ſide, he that is in his owne conceipt come to a full point, thinking that a little Religion, a little zeale, a little holines, a little knowledge will ſuffice, the ſame man hath no zeale, no holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16520:43"/> no knowledge, no religion at all. My rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, the euill ſeruant I ſpake of before, though in one place it is ſaide of him,<note place="margin">Math. 25.29.</note> that that was taken from him which he had, yet elſwhere it is ſaid of him, that that was taken from him <hi>which it ſeemed</hi> he had. So that it is but a ſeeming of Religion,<note place="margin">Luc. 8.18.</note> where there is no care of encreaſing. And thus at laſt I haue ended this Text, &amp; though I haue not hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led euery point ſo largely, as the worth of it did deſerue, yet I haue, in ſome meaſure, touched euery particular incident to this place.</p>
               <trailer>The ende of the ſecond Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <closer>Let God alone haue the glorie.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16520:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
